<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse of schism by that learned gentleman Edward Polhill, Esq. ...</title>
            <author>Polhill, Edward, 1622-1694?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 137 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55303</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2752</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3219</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12375295</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12375295</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60567</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55303)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60567)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 221:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse of schism by that learned gentleman Edward Polhill, Esq. ...</title>
                  <author>Polhill, Edward, 1622-1694?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 104, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Cockerill ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement on p. [1] at beginning and p. [1]-[2] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Schism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:60567:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60567:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Books Publiſhed by <hi>Edward Polhill</hi> of <hi>Burwaſh</hi> in <hi>Suſſex,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>, And Sold by <hi>Thomas Cockerill</hi> at the <hi>Three Legs,</hi> over-againſt the <hi>Stocks-Market.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>PRecious Faith conſidered in its Nature, Working, and Growth. In 8v<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Speculum Theologiae in Chricto:</hi> Or, a view of ſome Divine Truths, which are either Practically exemplified in Jeſus Chriſt, ſet forth in the Goſpel, or may be reaſonably deduced from thence. In 4t<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſtus in Corde:</hi> Or the Myſtical Union between Chriſt and Believers, conſider'd in its Reſemblances, Bonds, Seals, Privileges and Marks. In 8v<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe of Schiſm.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60567:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE OF SCHISM.</p>
            <p>By that Learned Gentleman, EDWARD POLHILL, <abbr>Eſq</abbr>, Late of <hi>Burwaſh</hi> in <hi>Suſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Cockerill,</hi> at the <hi>Three Legs,</hi> over-againſt the <hi>Stocks-Market.</hi> MDCXCIV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:60567:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60567:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>'TIS not the deſign of this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to commend the Author of the enſuing Treatiſe; his own <hi>Works</hi> do that ſufficiently. He was a very <hi>Learned Gentleman,</hi> and a <hi>Juſtice of the Peace,</hi> of very great eſteem among all men in his own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, where he lived <hi>in full and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Communion with the Church of</hi> England. And therefore being no <hi>Clergy-man</hi> either of one ſort or t'other, he is the more likely to write <hi>impartially</hi> about <hi>Schiſm;</hi> and being no Frequenter of any of the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> Meetings, he cannot reaſonably be ſuppoſed to be <hi>byaſs'd in their favour.</hi> But yet on the other hand, he was far enough from entertaining any of thoſe <hi>Prejudices</hi> againſt their Perſons or Aſſemblies, which it hath been
<pb facs="tcp:60567:4"/>the great endeavour of ſome to infuſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the minds of all men, but eſpecially of the Magiſtracy and Gentry. He was zealouſly concerned for Truth and Seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Religion, not for a Party. On all occaſions he ſhew'd himſelf to be one of a <hi>truly Chriſtian</hi> (that is, of a <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi>) Temper, and was a ſincere lover of <hi>all good men,</hi> of what <hi>Perſuaſion</hi> ſoever. He was fully convinced, and ſo wilt thou too, if thou diligently peruſeſt and readeſt the following Diſcourſe, that <hi>Bigotry</hi> is <hi>the dangerous Schiſm,</hi> the guilt whereof a man is not neceſſarily involved in, or ſecured from, by the bare <hi>being of this or that Party</hi> among us.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60567:4"/>
            <head>CHAP. I.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>The Church-Catholick two-fold, The ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry myſtical Body of Chriſt, or The <hi>totum integrale</hi> made up of all the Particular Churches. The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Church a Divine thing: Doth not conſiſt in Human Rites; in a Liturgy; Dioceſan Epiſcopacy, or the Civil Laws of Magiſtrates. Its true <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity in its internal Eſſence, and external Communion. A parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>CHriſtians, as high motives as they have to Unity, are yet divided, not only by the <hi>exiſtence</hi> of <hi>Schiſm,</hi> but about the <hi>notion</hi> of it. The <hi>Papiſt</hi> charges it on the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant;</hi> one <hi>Proteſtant</hi> charges it on another; and the Reaſon is, becauſe they differ in their meaſures of <hi>Church-<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</hi> Some require more to it than others; the <hi>Papiſt</hi> will have the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a Viſible Head; ſome <hi>Proteſtants</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:60567:5"/>will have an Unity of Human Rites and Modes: Hence there comes a <hi>Schiſm about Schiſm.</hi> The very <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> divides us. In this caſe it is worth the while to enquire into the true nature of Schiſm; in the doing of which two things muſt be premiſed. Something muſt be ſpoken of the <hi>Church;</hi> and ſomething of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Something muſt be ſpoken of the Church. In the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> we have <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which is a word derived from Congregating; in the <hi>New</hi> we have <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is a word derived from <hi>Evocating,</hi> or calling out. The <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church being ſhut up in one Nation could meet all together in one place; the Chriſtian Church being ſpread over the World, cannot indeed meet all together in one place, but they are <hi>coetus evocatus,</hi> a company called out of the World to the Worſhip of God. The Church may be conſidered as <hi>Catholick,</hi> or <hi>Particular.</hi> The <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick</hi> Church may be taken, either as <hi>the very myſtical Body</hi> of Chriſt, or
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:60567:5"/>as a <hi>totum integrale</hi> to all the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Churches on Earth. As the <hi>myſtical Body</hi> of Chriſt it is <hi>inviſible,</hi> made up only of <hi>real Saints;</hi> all of them are internally united to Chriſt the Head; all are animated by the Holy Spirit; all have the Joints and Bands of Grace; all have the effectual working in their hearts. This is the <hi>Church-Catholick</hi> in the Creed; this is the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Aſſembly of the firſt-born,</hi> Hebr. 12.23. This is in <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Congregation of the Elect.</hi> Here are no <hi>damnata mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra,</hi> as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeaks. As Chriſt's natural Body did conſiſt all of pure Members, ſo this myſtical Body doth conſiſt of true Believers. As in every Member of the natural Body there is an Human Spirit, ſo in every Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the myſtical Body there is the Spirit of Chriſt. Such is the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church, as it is the myſtical Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt. But as it is a <hi>totum inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grale,</hi> made up of all the <hi>particular Churches</hi> on Earth; ſo it is, as its parts are, <hi>viſible;</hi> and made up of <hi>good and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60567:6"/>bad.</hi> Some are living Members, Partakers of the Spirit of Chriſt; ſome are dead ones: Some are in internal conjunction with Chriſt, ſome are in external only: Some are in the Church really, and before God; ſome are in it only apparently, and before men. Thus the Church is a Field which hath Wheat and Tares; a Net, which hath good Fiſh and Bad; a Floor, which hath Corn and Chaff. In <hi>Iſaac</hi>'s Family there was an <hi>Eſau;</hi> in the Colledge of Apoſtles, a <hi>Judas;</hi> in the viſible Church there are fooliſh Virgins as well as wiſe; ſome have only the Lamps of Profeſſion, whilſt others have the Oyl of Grace. This may ſerve for the Church-Catholick. Now <hi>particular Churches</hi> are but <hi>partes ſimilares Eccleſiae Catholicae, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milar parts of the Catholick Church viſible.</hi> The <hi>Catholick</hi> Church is as the <hi>whole Tree, Particular</hi> Churches are but <hi>Branches.</hi> That is the main Ocean; theſe are but Arms, and Creeks of it. To that (as Mr. <hi>Hud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> obſerves) the Promiſes and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:60567:6"/>primarily belong; to theſe they belong in a ſecondary way. That is the firſt receptacle of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, theſe derive them from that. In every particular Church there is (as St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſpeaks) <hi>Plebs Paſtori adunata, a People joined to a Paſtor</hi> for the performance of Divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. Here the Word is preached, the Sacraments are adminiſtred.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2dly,</hi> Something muſt be ſpoken of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Church.</hi> The Unity of the Church is that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Church is one. There are many Members, but one Body; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Sheep, but one Fold; many Stones, but one Building. The Apoſtle reckons up many Unities appertaining to the Church. There is <hi>one body, and one ſpirit, even as ye are called in one hope of your calling; one Lord, one faith, one baptiſm, one God and father of all.</hi> Here is <hi>unit as principii,</hi> one God that calls the Church: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitas termini,</hi> one Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven that is hoped for by it: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitas mediorum,</hi> one Faith, one Baptiſm,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:60567:7"/>to join men to Chriſt, and the Church: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitas Capitis,</hi> one Lord Jeſus, who is the vital Head of the Church: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitas Corporis,</hi> one Body, in which the Members do all adhere one to another, and to the Head: And <hi>unitas Spiritûs,</hi> one Holy Spirit to animate and actuate the whole Body.</p>
            <p>The Unity of the Church is not an <hi>Human</hi> thing, but <hi>Divine.</hi> The Unity is as the Church is, <hi>built upon the foundations of the Apoſtles and Prophets,</hi> Eph. 2.20. All the <hi>Joints</hi> and <hi>Bands</hi> which tie the Church to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, are from <hi>Chriſt the Head.</hi> As under the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> God or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained the Loops and the Taches, that coupled the Curtains together, to make one Tabernacle, <hi>Exod.</hi> 26.6. So under the <hi>New,</hi> Chriſt hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained the <hi>Bands</hi> and <hi>Ligatures,</hi> that couple Believers together, to make one Church: Hence this Unity is ſtiled by St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. ad <hi>Cornel.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitas à Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no, &amp; per Apoſtolos tradita: An <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty delivered from the Lord Chriſt, and by the Apoſtles;</hi> and by St. <hi>Auſtin,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60567:7"/>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitas Chriſti, the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Contra <hi>Creſc.</hi> l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>31.</hi> l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> St. <hi>Jerom,</hi> ſpeaking of the Church of Chriſt as joined together in the unity of the Spirit, hath this notable Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage. <hi>Eccleſia habet urbes legis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Com. in <hi>Mich.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetarum, Evangelii, Apoſtoloram: Non eſt egreſſa de finibus ſuis, id eſt, de Scripturis Sanctis. The Church hath its Cities, the Law the Prophets, the Goſpel, the Apoſtles, it goeth not out of its bounds the Holy Scriptures.</hi> That only is Unity which is found there. When the queſtion was between the <hi>Catholicks</hi> and <hi>Donatiſts, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi ſit Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia? Where is the Church;</hi> the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumba unica,</hi> the <hi>Dove</hi> that <hi>is but one?</hi> St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> tells them,<note place="margin">De Unit. Eccl. c. <hi>2,</hi> &amp; <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> that it was to be ſought, <hi>Non in verbis noſtris, ſed in verbis Capitis; Not in our words, but in the words of the Head.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt the Head knew his own Body: And again, <hi>Sunt certe libri Dominici, ibi quaeramus Eccleſiam: There are the Lord's Books, there let us ſeek the Church:</hi> And again, <hi>Nolo Humanis Documentis, ſed Divinis Oraculis San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctam Eccleſiam demonſtrari. I will not have the Holy Church demonſtrated by
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60567:8"/>Human Documents, but by Divine Oracles.</hi> It was the notable Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of <hi>Beſſarion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fuit aliquando tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus quo immaculata Dei Spoaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Eccleſia ſummâ concordiâ tranquilliſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mâ pace, &amp; intemera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tâ veritate fruebatur, cum ſimplicitatem, &amp; puritatem Evangelicae Doctrinae maximi om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes faciebamus, ſolis Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cris eloquiis contenti, his inhaerentes, his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſcentes, in unum ab his collecti ovile ſub u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no Paſtore omnes agen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. <hi>Crab.</hi> Conc. <hi>Florent.</hi>
               </note> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Nice, That then the Church had the higheſt concord, peace and truth, when it did adhere to the ſimplicity and purity of the Evangelical Doctrine, contented with the Sacred Oracles, inhereing and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſcing in them only, collected by them into one fold, and living under one Paſtor.</hi> The only true Unity of the Church is that which is to be found in Scripture. When men will have an Unity not <hi>of God's making,</hi> but <hi>of their own,</hi> it falls out as when <hi>a piece of new cloth is put to an old Garment,</hi> there is a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>rent</hi> made. The Humane thing that did ſeem to fill up the Churches Unity, doth make a breach in it. <hi>Victor</hi> will have <hi>one Eaſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi> and this little thing rents off the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Churches from the <hi>Weſtern.</hi> The Unity of a viſible Head in the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:60567:8"/>Church is very plauſible, yet this is but a piece of <hi>Donatiſm</hi> to have the Church only <hi>in parte Papae.</hi> 'Tis (as <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaid againſt <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople</hi>) <hi>Titulus in diſciſſionem Eccleſiae, a Title to rent the Church in pieces.</hi> Nay, the very <hi>Roman</hi> Church (where it was hatched) is rent by it. Part would have a Council a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Pope: Part would have the Pope above a Council. The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils of <hi>Conſtance</hi> and <hi>Baſil</hi> call the Popes Schiſmaticks, and the Popes have caſt off and reprobated thoſe Councils. Thus thoſe Human things in the Church, which are ſet up for Unity, turn to <hi>Ataxie;</hi> and like the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Reed, pierce and rent that hand that leans on them.</p>
            <p>Theſe things being ſo, it appears that the Unity of the Church doth not conſiſt in any Human thing. But to inſtance in ſome particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1ſt.</hi> It doth not ſtand in <hi>Human Rites and Obſervations.</hi> In the firſt Golden Age (in which, as <hi>Egeſippus</hi> ſaith the Church continued a <hi>pure
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60567:9"/>Virgin</hi>) there was little or nothing of Ceremony, but much of Unity. Chriſtians were then <hi>of one heart, and of one ſoul,</hi> Acts 4.32. In after Ages Human Obſervations creeping into the Church, they were obſerved <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riè &amp; pro arbitrio.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſeb. <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 23.</note> Chriſtians varied in the obſervation of <hi>Eaſter;</hi> ſome kept <hi>Eaſter</hi> on one day, ſome on another. They varied in their obſervation of <hi>Lent.</hi> Some faſted one day, ſome two, ſome more, ſome forty. They varied not only in the number of the days, but in their abſtinence. Some eat Fowl with their Fiſh;<note place="margin">Socrat. <hi>Hiſt. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 21.</note> ſome were contented with dry bread only. They varied alſo in many other Human Obſervations, as may be ſeen in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Story. In all theſe there was <hi>no unity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Soz. <hi>Hiſt. l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 19.</note> yet the <hi>true <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> was not wanting. They did not put uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in ſuch things, no; the Rule was, <hi>Differentia rituum commendat unitatem fidei, The non-unity in Rites commended the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Faith.</hi> The Chriſtians were wont to faſt,<note place="margin">Tert. <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra</hi> Pſych.</note> 
               <hi>ex arbitrio, non ex imperio;</hi> out of <hi>choice,</hi> not out of <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</hi> St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. <hi>118.</hi>
               </note> ſpeaking of the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60567:9"/>various Cuſtoms in the Church, ſaith, that in ſuch kind of things there was <hi>libera obſervatio;</hi> indifferent things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained indifferent; one did not impoſe them upon another; ſo there was no breach of Unity. When the queſtion was, whether there ſhould be in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm <hi>trina</hi> or <hi>ſimplex merſio;</hi> St. <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> anſwered,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conc.</hi> To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let. 4. <hi>Can.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>In unâ Fide nihil officit diverſa conſuetudo; In one Faith a di verſe Cuſtom hurts not.</hi> In the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Lateran</hi> under Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the Third, <hi>Can.</hi> 9. it is ordained, That <hi>where in one City, or Dioceſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Crab.</hi> Conc. Tom. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>there were people of divers Tongues and Rites,</hi> ſub unâ Fide, <hi>there the Divine Offices ſhould be performed,</hi> ſecundum diverſitates Rituum &amp; Linguarum <hi>Luther,</hi> ſpeaking of the Popiſh Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, ſaith truly, <hi>Sub Papâ eſt pompa externae unitatis, ſed intus non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n ſi confuſiſſima Babylon. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder the Pope is the pomp of external <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, but within there is nothing but a moſt confuſed Babel.</hi> It is certain Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unity doth not conſiſt in Rites; let men fancy what they will, there is but <hi>one healing Rule</hi> to be found, <hi>In
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60567:10"/>neceſſariis unitas, in non-neceſſariis libertas, in utriſque charitas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2dly.</hi> It doth not ſtand in a <hi>Liturgy,</hi> or preſcribed Form of Prayer. The Church for ſome Centuries was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Liturgy, but never without Unity. The Liturgies aſcribed to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> St. <hi>James,</hi> St. <hi>Mark,</hi> are plainly ſpurious; there are to be found the words <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which were not extant in the firſt Centuries. There mention is made of <hi>Temples, Altars, Monaſteries,</hi> ſuch things as the Primitive Church knew not.<note place="margin">Apol. <hi>2.</hi> prope fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem. <hi>Tert.</hi> Ap. cap. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> In <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi>'s time the Miniſter prayed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>according to his ability.</hi> In <hi>Tertullian</hi>'s he prayed, <hi>Sine monitore quia de pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctore, without any Prompter but their own heart.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt <hi>34.</hi> de Celer.</note> In St. <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s time the Eccleſiaſtical Lector was to read <hi>prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepta &amp; Evangelium Domini,</hi> not a Liturgy.<note place="margin">Euſeb. <hi>de Vit.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 20.</note> In <hi>Conſtantin</hi>'s time, had there been a Liturgy, he had not needed to have compoſed a Prayer for his Army.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Soc.</hi> Eccleſ. Hiſt. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> In the time of <hi>Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> among all Forms of Religion,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60567:10"/>there were not two that conſented together <hi>in precandi more.</hi> Set-forms of Prayer were not introduced into the Church, till the <hi>Arian</hi> and <hi>Pela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gian</hi> Hereſies invaded it, and then to prevent the diffuſion of Heretical Poyſon, Set-forms came in. In the Council of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> holden about the Year 368. <hi>Can.</hi> 18. it was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, that there ſhould be <hi>caedem preces:</hi> But this was a Form of the <hi>Miniſter's own compoſing,</hi> as appears by the <hi>23d</hi> Canon of the Third Council of <hi>Carthage,</hi> holden about the Year 399. which appointed that none ſhould uſe a Form, unleſs he did firſt <hi>conferre cum fratribus inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctioribus.</hi> After which, in the <hi>Mile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitan</hi> Concil, holden about the Year 416. <hi>Can.</hi> 12. it was ordained, that the <hi>Form</hi> uſed ſhould be <hi>approved of in a Synod:</hi> Still this was a Form of the Miniſter's own making. It was many years after this before a Liturgy was abſolutely <hi>impoſed</hi> on Miniſters, that they might not pray by their own Gifts only, but by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed Forms of others. About the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60567:11"/>Year 800. <hi>Charles the Great</hi> being Emperor, Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> moved him to <hi>eſtabliſh a Liturgy</hi> by a Civil Edict, and obtained it: And this is ſaid to be <hi>Gregory's Liturgy.</hi> Thus the Church was much longer without a Liturgy than it can be imagined to have been without Unity. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Unity doth not conſiſt in it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly.</hi> It doth not ſtand (as I take it) in a <hi>Dioceſan Epiſcopacy.</hi> There are <hi>Biſhops</hi> in Scripture, but no <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſan</hi> ones. There are <hi>Presbyters or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained in every City,</hi> but no <hi>Biſhops</hi> ordained to be over them. In <hi>Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonica</hi> there were <hi>not one,</hi> but <hi>many</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.12. The Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidency there was in <hi>many,</hi> not in <hi>one.</hi> The Biſhops at <hi>Philippi,</hi> Phil. 1.1. being <hi>more than one in one city,</hi> were no other than Presbyters. The <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters</hi> at <hi>Epheſus</hi> are in expreſs terms called <hi>Biſhops,</hi> Acts 20.17, <hi>&amp;</hi> 28. St. <hi>Peter</hi> exhorts the <hi>Presbyters</hi> to feed the Flock of God, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>acting as Biſhops</hi> among them, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.2. St. <hi>Paul</hi> would have <hi>Titus</hi> ordain
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:60567:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Presbyters in every City, for a Biſhop</hi> muſt be ſo and ſo. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5, 7. If the <hi>Biſhop</hi> and <hi>Presbyter</hi> were not here the <hi>ſame,</hi> the reaſon, which muſt not be imagined, would be inconſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial. There are the qualifying Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters of a <hi>Biſhop</hi> ſet down in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. and in <hi>Titus</hi> 1.7. but there is not one of them but is requiſite in a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> not one of them <hi>peculiar to a Dioceſan Biſhop.</hi> The Scripture Evidence is very clear, that a Biſhop and a Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter are all one. When <hi>Aerius</hi> brought ſome of theſe Scriptures to prove it, <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> who calls him <hi>Heretick,</hi> gives only this poor Anſwer, That <hi>in many Churches there were no Presbyters;</hi> but who can believe that at that time there were more Biſhops than Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; that, when there were more Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops in one City, there ſhould be no Presbyters at all there. It is a thing altogether incredible. <hi>Clemens,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Salm.</hi> in App. ad Primat. fol. <hi>50, 54.</hi>
               </note> in his <hi>Epiſtle to the Corinthians,</hi> makes Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Presbyters all one. <hi>Polycarp,</hi> in his <hi>Epiſtle to the Philippians,</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions only <hi>Presbyters and Deacons.</hi> In the Epiſtle aſcribed to <hi>Ignatius ad Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſios,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:60567:12"/>a Biſhop above a Presbyter is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Salm. <hi>in App. fol.</hi> 57. <hi>Com. in</hi> 1 Tim. 3.</note> a <hi>novel Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith, <hi>Epiſcopi &amp; Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteri una ordinatio eſt,</hi> there is <hi>but one ordination of a Biſhop and a Presbyter.</hi> St. <hi>Jerome</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad <hi>Ocean.</hi> &amp; ad <hi>Evagr.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Apud veteres iidem Epiſcopi &amp; Presbyteri fuerunt. Ancient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Biſhops and Presbyters were the ſame.</hi> Again,<note place="margin">Com. in Epiſt. <hi>Tit.</hi>
               </note> That the <hi>Biſhop was greater than the Presbyter,</hi> conſuetudine magis quam Dominicae diſpoſitionis veritate, <hi>rather by cuſtom, than by any true di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſation from the Lord:</hi> And again, that before, <hi>Communi Presbyterorum Conſilio Eccleſiae gubernabantur. The Churches were ruled by the Common Council of Presbyters.</hi> St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, that Epiſcopacy is greater than Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery, <hi>Secundum honorum vocabula,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quae jam Eccleſiae uſus obtinuit, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Titles of Honour which are now uſed in the Church.</hi> Thus it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears that a <hi>Dioceſan</hi> Epiſcopacy is but <hi>Humane,</hi> and by conſequence Church-unity doth not ſtand in it. The Reformed Churches which are without Epiſcopacy, are not without Unity. I conclude this with the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60567:12"/>of the Learned Dr. <hi>Ward,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Determ. <hi>109.</hi>
               </note> who (ſpeaking of the difference in Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Government which is between our Church and thoſe beyond Sea) ſaith, that it may, and ought to be <hi>tolerated,</hi> abſque fraternae unitatis lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione, <hi>without any breach of Brotherly unity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>4thly.</hi> It doth not ſtand in <hi>the Civil Laws of Princes.</hi> When Magiſtrates were <hi>Pagans,</hi> there was yet a Church, and an Unity in it. When they became Chriſtians, the Unity was the ſame, the Joints and the Bands were as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>ſacred,</hi> not <hi>civil;</hi> from <hi>Chriſt</hi> the Head, not from the <hi>Magiſtrate.</hi> It's true, the Church hath an external help and guard from good Laws, but its Unity doth not conſiſt in them. <hi>Neque quia regna dividuntur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Unitate Eccleſ. c. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ideo &amp; Chriſtiana unitas dividitur, cum in utraque parte inveniatur Catholica Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Auſtin, Kingdoms may be divided, but Chriſtian <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity is not; in both parts the Catholick Church is found.</hi> Should the Unity of the Church conſiſt in the Laws of Magiſtrates,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:60567:13"/>then the Laws being diſſolved, there would be no Unity; the Laws being altered, the Unity muſt vary, and turn about to every point, as the Laws do. That which now is Unity, under a contrary Law muſt be Schiſm; that which now is a Schiſm, under a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Law may be Unity. Under the Emperor <hi>Valentinian,</hi> the Orthodox may be the Church; under <hi>Valens,</hi> the <hi>Arrians</hi> may be it. Nay, as the Magiſtrate may be, you ſhall not know by him where the Church or the Truth is. In that great Schiſm, when the Biſhops of the <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt</hi> fell out about the Council of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> ſome would not part with a ſyllable of it, ſome utterly rejected it: The Emperor <hi>Anaſtaſius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Magd. <hi>Cent.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. Evagr. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 30.</note> 
               <hi>Aulicâ Sapientiâ uſus,</hi> baniſhed ſome of both Parties, <hi>aequale praemium veritas &amp; mendacium tulêre, Truth and Falſehood were alike rewarded.</hi> Hence it appears, that the Unity of the Church doth not ſtand in Humane Laws, the true Unity is founded only in Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:60567:13"/>
Theſe things being ſo, I come to lay down the true Unity. The Church may be conſidered, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in its <hi>inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Eſſence,</hi> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in its <hi>external Communion.</hi> In the firſt conſideration it hath <hi>inviſible Bands</hi> to make it one; in the ſecond it hath <hi>viſible</hi> ones. The ſoul of the Church is, (as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeaks) internal Grace, the Body of it is external Profeſſion and Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
            <p>Take the Church in its <hi>internal Eſſence,</hi> ſo its Unity ſtands in the Holy Spirit, and the Graces of it. <hi>There is one body, and one ſpirit,</hi> Eph. 4.4. There are many Members in the Myſtical Body of Chriſt, but they are all but one Body; and why ſo? They are diſtant in place and time, yet they are but <hi>one Body;</hi> diſtinct Bodies have diſtinct Spirits, but they have but <hi>one Holy Spirit,</hi> which unites them not only to Chriſt the Head, but one to another; ſo they muſt be but one Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, becauſe they have but one Spirit to actuate them. Hence St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, <hi>Non poteſt vivere Corpus Chriſti niſi de Spiritu Chriſti,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In <hi>Joh.</hi> Tract. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The Body of Chriſt can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:60567:14"/>live but by the Spirit of Chriſt.</hi> It is the Holy Spirit that makes them one living Body.</p>
            <p>Under the Spirit there are three Uniting Graces which make the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Church but one; they are <hi>Faith, Hope,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Enarr. in <hi>Pſal. 37.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and Charity.</hi> Hence that of St. <hi>Auſtin, Si Fides noſtra ſincera ſit, &amp; Spes certa, &amp; Charitas accenſa, ſumus in Corpore Chriſti. If our Faith be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, our Hope certain, our Charity kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, then are we in the Body of Chriſt.</hi> Hence St. <hi>Bernard</hi> obſerves a triple Vertue in the Primitive Church,<note place="margin">De aſcenſi Domini, Serm. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Magnanimity, Longanimity, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity;</hi> the firſt was from <hi>Faith,</hi> the ſecond from <hi>Hope,</hi> the third from <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</hi> Faith unites all the Members in the Myſtical Body to Chriſt the Head, and ſo they are <hi>one in Capite.</hi> Love unites them not only to the Head, but one to another, and ſo they are <hi>one in Corpore.</hi> Hope unites them to one cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in Heaven, and ſo they are <hi>one in Termino.</hi> In theſe things ſtands the Unity of the Church in its internal Eſſence.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:60567:14"/>
Take the Church in its <hi>External Communion,</hi> ſo its Unity ſtands <hi>in the Holy Ordinances. They continued ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly in the Apoſtles doctrine, and fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, and in breaking of bread, and in prayers,</hi> Acts 2.42. Theſe are the golden Bands that tie the Church to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. As the Church <hi>myſtical</hi> is made one by <hi>Graces,</hi> ſo the Church <hi>viſible</hi> is made one by <hi>Ordinances:</hi> As the ſame Graces are all over the one, ſo the ſame Ordinances are all over the other.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſame pure word</hi> is preached.<note place="margin">Com. in <hi>Pſal. 133.</hi>
               </note> The Church (ſaith St. <hi>Jerome</hi>) <hi>Non in parietibus ſed in dogmatum veritate conſiſtit, It doth not ſtand in Walls, but in True Doctrines. The Hereticks,</hi> as the ſame Father goes on, <hi>may have the Walls, but the Church is where the Truth is.</hi> The <hi>Arians</hi> boaſted of their Unity,<note place="margin">Contra <hi>Auxent.</hi>
               </note> but as St. <hi>Hilary</hi> tells them, it was but <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nit as Impiet at is, an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of Impiety.</hi> The Unity of Truth is in the Church only; there all have one Law, one Charter; all are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>concorporated and copart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the promiſe,</hi> Eph. 3.6. No
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60567:15"/>body of men hath ſuch a Law or <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> as the Church hath.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſame Sacraments</hi> are admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred. Theſe are Seals of the Churches Charter, and Symbols of that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion which we have with Chriſt as Head, and one with another as Fellow-members. In Baptiſm we enter into the Holy Society; in the Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per we are Fellow-commoners, and eat together as Members of the ſame Family.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Contra</hi> Fauſt. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nich. <hi>l.</hi> 19. <hi>cap.</hi> 11.</note> St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, That <hi>in every Religion men are joined together,</hi> aliquo ſignaculorum conſortio, <hi>by a fellowſhip in ſome Seals.</hi> No Society of men hath ſuch Seals as the Church hath.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſame Prayers</hi> in <hi>ſubſtance</hi> are made; tho in the Primitive times there was <hi>no Common Prayer,</hi> or <hi>Liturgy</hi> in the Church,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ignatius,</hi> Epiſt. ad Magn.</note> yet there was ever <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a Common,</hi> that is, <hi>a Publick Prayer,</hi> which in the mouth of the Miniſter is as it were breathed out by all the people, that the Divine Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing may come down upon the Word and Sacraments.</p>
            <p>I ſhall here add nothing touching <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Diſcipline,</hi> becauſe the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60567:15"/>particular <hi>mode</hi> of it is not <hi>ſo eſſential to a Church</hi> as the other are.</p>
            <p>To conclude, <hi>Where there are law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Paſtors diſpenſing Holy Ordinances, and a People meeting, and unanimouſly joining in the uſe of them, there is a True Church;</hi> Hic eſt fons Veritatis, hoc Templum Dei, hoc domicilium Fidei, as <hi>Lactantius</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>There is the Fountain of Truth, the Temple of God, the Dwelling-place of Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things being premiſed touching the Church, and its Unity; I come now to enquire into the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Schiſm.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:60567:16"/>
            <head>CHAP. II.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Schiſm defined. Seminal or Actual. In the Church, or from it: There may be a Schiſm without Separation; and a Separation without Schiſm. The Characters of Schiſmatical Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Voluntarineſs, want of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Pride, Error, breach of Sacred <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, for little or no Cauſe, from the Catholick Church.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>SChiſm is the <hi>Sciſſure of the Church viſible, a breach of the ſacred <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of it without cauſe.</hi> 'Tis a <hi>Sciſſure of the Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Unitat. Eccleſ.</note> a renting, <hi>veſtem Chriſti inconſutilem, the ſeamleſs Coat of Chriſt,</hi> as St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſpeaks. It was (as St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> ſpeaks) <hi>ſignified by the breaking of the net,</hi> Luke 5.6. <hi>The net at Sea brake,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibi Eccleſia in hocſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo, hic in fine ſeculi figurata eſt <hi>Auſtin</hi> in <hi>Joh. Tract.</hi> 122.</note> propter ſignificanda Schiſmata, <hi>to note out the Schiſms of the Church on Earth;</hi> but the Net drawn to the Shore <hi>brake not, John</hi> 21.11. to note out, that the Saints in Heaven are, <hi>in ſummâ pace,</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:60567:16"/>in the higheſt unity. No Schiſms are in that bleſſed Region.</p>
            <p>'Tis a Sciſſure of the <hi>Church Viſible.</hi> In the Church <hi>Myſtical</hi> there are no Schiſms. It's true, <hi>the Fleſh</hi> (which in the Saints warreth againſt the Spirit) is a <hi>Schiſmatick,</hi> and makes ſuch rents in their Souls, that they are in a ſort divided from themſelves. <hi>It is not I, but ſin that dwelleth in me,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 7.20. He diſtinguiſheth his corrupt Self from his renewed Self. But yet that Fleſh cannot, ſhall not totally, finally rent them off from the Myſtical Body. They may fall into ſins, yet thoſe Principles which tie them to the Myſtical Body, are not extinct; the Spirit of Grace will not leave them, but raiſe them up out of their Falls. Hence St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In</hi> Pſal. 88.</note> 
               <hi>Si in aeternum caput, in aeternum &amp; mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra, If Chriſt the head be for ever, ſo are the Members.</hi> Schiſm then is not in the Church <hi>Myſtical,</hi> but in the Church <hi>Viſible.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis a breach of the <hi>Sacred <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> in the Church, I mean of an Unity <hi>found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Scripture;</hi> every breach of that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60567:17"/>Unity is Schiſm; but a breach of an <hi>Human Canon or Law</hi> is <hi>not Schiſm.</hi> St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> (ſhewing the madneſs of Schiſmaticks) ſaith,<note place="margin">De Unit. Eccl.</note> 
               <hi>Quis audeat ſcin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitatem Dei? Who dares cut in pieces the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of God?</hi> So he calls the Churches Unity, becauſe it is not Humane.<note place="margin">Contra <hi>Creſc.</hi> l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, <hi>It is a great evil to make a Schiſm, ab <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitate Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti,</hi> not from man's Unity, but from <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s; and the ſame Author calls Schiſm in divers places,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Contr.</hi> Lit. Pet. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 30, 81.</note> 
               <hi>Sacrilegium Schiſmatis, the Sacriledge of Schiſm,</hi> becauſe the Unity is not Human, but Divine. When the Papiſts charge Schiſm upon us, as caſting off the Pope the Head of Unity, the Learned Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> anſwers,<note place="margin">Tract of Schiſm, 157.</note> 
               <hi>He was never appointed by Chriſt to be Head;</hi> and the Anſwer is ſound, No ſuch Unity was appointed in Scripture.</p>
            <p>Again, 'Tis a breach of the Sacred Unity <hi>without Cauſe.</hi> When the Orthodox Chriſtians ſeparated from <hi>Arian</hi> Biſhops, who ſubverted the Faith of Chriſt, it was no Schiſm at all. When the Proteſtants came out of Idolatrous <hi>Rome,</hi> it was no Schiſm,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:60567:17"/>but a Duty. <hi>Cauſa</hi> (ſay the Canoniſts) <hi>non ſeceſſio facit Schiſmaticum,</hi> it is <hi>not the ſeparation but the cauſe that makes the Schiſmatick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Schiſm is either <hi>ſeminal or actual. Seminal</hi> Schiſm ſtands in the carnal and corrupt Luſts of the Heart; theſe are the bitter Roots and Springs of Diviſion. <hi>Whence come wars and fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings among you? come they not of your luſts that war in your members?</hi> James 4.1. Were there no warring Luſts within, there would be no jarring Diſcords without. The Apoſtle, ſpeaking of the Diviſions in <hi>Corinth,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Are ye not carnal, and walk as men?</hi> 1 Cor. 3.3. Diviſions come from the Carnal part in Chriſtians, not from the Spiritual. St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s dividing the Beaſts, but not the Birds, ſaith by way of alluſion,<note place="margin">De Civ. lib. <hi>16.</hi> cap. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Carnales inter ſe dividun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, Spirituales nullo modo, Carnal men are divided one from another, but not ſpiritual.</hi> The Luſts of men are the great Make-bates. But to inſtance in ſome particulars. <hi>Pride</hi> is an horrible Schiſmatick; by ſwelling it breaks in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:60567:18"/>a rupture; by lifting up a man above himſelf, it divides him from his Brother. The greateſt inſtance of Pride in the World is the Biſhop of <hi>Rome;</hi> he ſits, as he pretends, in the Infallible Chair; he hath all Laws <hi>in ſcrinio pectoris;</hi> he claims all Power, Sacerdotal and Regal; he ſtiles him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the Head of the whole Church; he is called <hi>a God on Earth;</hi> his Title is, <hi>Dominus Deus noſter Papa;</hi> and after all this ſtate, he is no leſs an Inſtance of Schiſm than of Pride. He rents himſelf off from the Church Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal; he will not be a Member in it, but an Head, a Univerſal Lord over it. The Church muſt be only <hi>in parte Papae,</hi> and no-where elſe. All the Proteſtant Churches in the World muſt be caſt off as Schiſmaticks, and this abominable Schiſm muſt be ſtiled Unity. Again, <hi>Self-love</hi> is a great Schiſmatick; it ſo appropriates all to it ſelf, that it leaves nothing in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon; it is ſuch an inordinate uniting of a man to himſelf, that he cannot be joined to others. That little word <hi>(Ego)</hi> is a ſtrange divider of all Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:60567:18"/>When <hi>Novatus</hi> fell off from the Church, and became the Head of the <hi>Cathari,</hi> there was ſomewhat of <hi>ſelf</hi> in it.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſeb.</hi> Eccl. Hiſt. l. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>42.</hi>
               </note> The denial of an Epiſcopal Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment made him ſet up a Church for himſelf; and in that Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he gave the Euchariſt, he made the Communicants ſwear by the Body and Blood of Chriſt not to forſake him. To name but one thing more, <hi>Hatred</hi> is alſo an inward Schiſmatick; it diſſolves what Love unites, and ſets a man againſt his Brother, to whom he ſhould be joined in amity.<note place="margin">De Bapt. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Origo Schiſmatis eſt odium fraternum,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Auſtin, The hatred of a Brother is the origin of Schiſm.</hi> In the Council at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> called <hi>Concilium praedato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium,</hi> the <hi>Eutychian</hi> hatred broke out ſadly againſt the Orthodox. The Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops that favoured that Hereſy, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the matter by mere force and violence, crying out, <hi>Qui dicit duas Naturas, in duo dividit. He that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth two Natures in Chriſt, divides him into two.</hi> Such a deſperate thing is Hatred, that it prompts men to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide even unto blood. Such Luſts as
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:60567:19"/>theſe are the roots of gall and worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, which bear the bitter fruits of Schiſm and Diviſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Actual</hi> Schiſm is either a <hi>Schiſm in the Church,</hi> or a <hi>Schſm from it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Schiſm <hi>in the Church</hi> ſtands in the Differences and Diſſentions of the Members in it. We have in the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> three inſtances of it. They differed about the Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of their Teachers. <hi>Every one of you ſaith, I am of Paul, and I of Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los, and I of Cephas,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.12. They differed about the manner and time of the Holy Euchariſt. <hi>They did not wait one for another, the rich contemned the poor,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.21, 22. They differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about the variety of Gifts among them; the inferior in gifts envied the ſuperior, and the ſuperior in gifts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed the inferior; the <hi>feet</hi> envied the <hi>hand,</hi> and the <hi>head</hi> undervalued the <hi>feet;</hi> 1 Cor. 12.15, <hi>&amp;</hi> 21. And every one of theſe differences is in theſe Texts called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a Schiſm</hi> in the Church; and the reaſon is, becauſe every one of them did break the Unity of the Church in Ordinances. When
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:60567:19"/>they lookt more on the Teacher, than on the Truth, there could not be an intire communion in hearing the pure word, they heard it but partially in the gifts of one, rather than of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. When at the Lord's Supper they did not wait for, but contemn one another, there could not be an unanimous conjunction in that Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance. The Euchariſt, the Seal and Bond of Union, was as it were rent and torn in pieces. When the inferior in gifts envied, and the ſuperior de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed, they could not worſhip and ſerve God like thoſe, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.1. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>with one accord.</hi> Thoſe Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences did make a breach upon that Worſhip that ſhould have been intire. Now here it is to be noted, that <hi>every difference</hi> among Chriſtians doth not amount to Schiſm. There was a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roxiſm,</hi> a hot fit between <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> yet <hi>no Schiſm,</hi> Acts 15.39. In the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> Brother went to law with Brother, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.6. The Apoſtle blames the difference, but calls it not Schiſm. <hi>Stephen,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> was againſt Rebaptization;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:60567:20"/>
               <hi>Cyprian,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Carthage,</hi> was for it;<note place="margin">De unico Bapt. c. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> yet there was no Schiſm; <hi>Ambo in unitate Catholica conſtituti,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Auſtin, both remained in Catholick unity.</hi> There were differences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> and <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Jerom</hi> and <hi>Auſtin,</hi> yet it would be hard to charge them with Schiſm. The <hi>Lutherans</hi> differ from the other Reformed Churches in ſome leſſer Truths; but becauſe they agree in fundamental Articles, there is not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly a Schiſm; the difference, <hi>non impedit,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>hinders not the unity of the Faith,</hi> ſaith Dr. <hi>Ward.</hi> But then Differences amount to Schiſm when they <hi>break the unity of Faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Determ. fol. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>or the unanimous Communion in Ordinances.</hi> Such were the Differences above-mentioned in <hi>Corinth;</hi> there was no ſeparation from the Church there; yet becauſe thoſe Differences broke the unity of Ordinances, they are called Schiſm.</p>
            <p>A Schiſm <hi>from the Church</hi> ſtands in a criminous ſeparation from it. The word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, when it relates to the Church, doth, as I take it, only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>note
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:60567:20"/>in Scripture, <hi>Diviſions in a Church.</hi> But the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, doth ſeem to denote diviſion <hi>from a Church.</hi> Such a kind of diſſention, in which men ſeparate one from another in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and place, as well as mind. Yet in that, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3. it ſeemeth to be no more than diviſion in a Church. However this be, the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Jud.</hi> 19. doth properly ſignify <hi>to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate,</hi> or put ones ſelf <hi>extra terminos Eccleſiae, out of the bounds of the Church.</hi> Now this Schiſm from a Church is either <hi>negative</hi> or <hi>poſitive. Negative</hi> Schiſm is, when men ſeparate from a Church, and go no further; no new Church or Aſſembly is ſet up. <hi>Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> Schiſm is, when there is not only a ſimple Separation, but a new Church or Aſſembly is inſtituted, in which the Word and Sacraments are admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred. This is called <hi>ſtruere Altare contra Altare.</hi> A <hi>negative</hi> Seceſſion may in ſome caſe be lawful, as when one is unjuſtly ejected out of a Church he may recede from it. Yet (ſaith the Learned <hi>Camero</hi>) a poſitive Seceſſion in that caſe is not lawful,<note place="margin">De Eccleſ. <hi>325.</hi>
               </note> he may not
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:60567:21"/>immediately ſet up a new Church, at leaſt not without ſome other Reaſons or Circumſtances.</p>
            <p>Touching this Separating Schiſm, it is firſt to be noted, that there may be a <hi>Schiſm without a Separation,</hi> and there may be a <hi>Separation without a Schiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There may be a <hi>Schiſm without a Separation, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> a <hi>Schiſm in the body,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.25. when there is no ſchiſm from it. There was not (for ought I can ſee) any Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration in the Church of <hi>Corinth.</hi> Yet the Diſſentions there making a breach upon the Communion in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, did amount to Schiſm. St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">De Unit. Eccl.</note> That <hi>all believers are in one Houſe,</hi> The Church, ſaith he, is <hi>unanimit at is hoſpitium, an Houſe of ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and unanimity,</hi> where they ſweetly dwell together in the unanimous Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Service of God. If a man do not go out of this Houſe, and leave the Unity of it; yet if he make Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentions there, and diſturb that Unity he is guilty of Schiſm.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:60567:21"/>
Again, There may be a <hi>Separation without a Schiſm.</hi> In many Caſes one part of a Congregation may depart from the other, and become a Church of it ſelf, and yet there may be no Schiſm at all. What if it be done in a Congregation too great to meet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for convenience, and by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon conſent? This will be no Schiſm at all. 'Tis but as when <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Lot</hi> parted aſunder, becauſe the Land was not able to bear them: Or, as when the Hive being too little for the Bees, one part goes away, and dwells by it ſelf in a new Family. What if there be a <hi>Law or Canon made to allow ſuch a Separation?</hi> It will hardly be called Schiſm; and yet Church-unity doth not vary as Human Laws and Canons do, for then it might be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing or nothing, as men pleaſe. If in a Church the foundations of the holy Faith be deſtroyed, what can the Righteous do? Join they cannot, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate they muſt. When <hi>Eunomius</hi> the <hi>Arian</hi> was made a Biſhop,<note place="margin">Theod. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 14.</note> not one of his Flock, rich or poor, young or old, man or woman, would commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:60567:22"/>with him in the Service of God, but left him to officiate alone. When <hi>Neſtorius</hi> did firſt publiſh his Hereſy in the Church, the people made a noiſe,<note place="margin">Evagr. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.</note> and ran out of the Aſſembly. When under the Emperor <hi>Baſiliſcus</hi> five hundred Biſhops condemned the Council of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> it was hard for Chriſtians to join with them. The Church is where the Truth is, and no where elſe. What if the <hi>terms of Communion be ſinful?</hi> we are rather to break with all Churches, than to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit one ſin againſt God. The break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off from him is more than break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off from all men. Thus in ſome caſes there may be a Separation with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Schiſm. Indeed Schiſm is not a mere <hi>local</hi> defection, but a <hi>moral</hi> one. <hi>Non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>liſceſſies corporalibus motibus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Bap. cont. <hi>Don.</hi> l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſed ſpirit alibus eſt metiendus,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin, The departure is not to be meaſured by corporal motions, but by ſpiritual:</hi> but enough of this.</p>
            <p>In the next place, I ſhall endeavour to lay down ſome <hi>Characters</hi> whereby it may be known when Separation is Schiſmatical.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:60567:22"/>
               <hi>1ſt.</hi> Schiſmatical Separation is <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentional, and perfectly voluntary.</hi> Thus the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>thoſe that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate themſelves,</hi> Jud. 19. do by their own voluntary act put themſelves out of the bounds of the Church. Thus they that <hi>went out</hi> of the Apoſtolical Church, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.19. did it intentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally and freely. It is the obſervation of <hi>Aquinas,</hi> That as in natural things,<note place="margin">2, 2ae. <hi>quaeſt.</hi> 39. <hi>Art.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi>
               </note> that which is <hi>by accident</hi> doth not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute the Species: So in moral, not that which is <hi>beſides the intention,</hi> for that is accidental; hence he infers, <hi>Peccatum Schiſmatis proprie eſt ſpeciale peccatum, ex eo quod intendit ſe ab uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate ſeparare quam charit as facit. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prie Schiſmatici dicuntur, qui propria ſponte &amp; intentione ſe ab unitate Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae ſeparant. The ſin of Schiſm is a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial ſin, in that it intends to ſeparate from that unity which charity makes. Schiſmaticks are properly thoſe, who of their own accord and intention do ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate themſelves from the unity of the Church.</hi> It's true, every Schiſmatick doth not ſay as <hi>Marcion</hi> did, <hi>Ego ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam Eccleſiam, I will cleave the Church
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:60567:23"/>in two;</hi> yet this is that which he <hi>means</hi> in his Separation. As in our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Law, when we would know whether an <hi>entry</hi> amount to a <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeiſin,</hi> we enquire,<note place="margin">Cro. <hi>lib.</hi> 3. Blunden.</note> 
               <hi>quo animo fecerit, with what mind it was done.</hi> So in Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy, if we would know whether a Separation amount unto Schiſm, we muſt enquire <hi>with what mind it was done.</hi> Schiſm, ſaith Dr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> is a <hi>voluntary dividing.</hi> The Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick is he that divides himſelf from the Church; not he that is cut off from it, but he that goes out, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedes of his own accord. He condemns himſelf, being out of the Church, not by Cenſure, but <hi>ſuo arbitrio,</hi> by his own free Choice. The <hi>Donatiſts</hi> were in their minds and wills ſo ſet upon their own way,<note place="margin">Auſt. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 162.</note> that after a long ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Debates and Hearings, they were ſtill the ſame as before. A right Schiſmatick makes it his buſineſs to divide;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cypr.</hi> de Unit. Eccl.</note> 
               <hi>A Matre Filios ſegregat, Oves à Paſtores ſolicitat; He ſevers the Sons from the Mother, he entices the Sheep from the Paſtor.</hi> This is the firſt Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:60567:23"/>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> Schiſmatical Separation pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from <hi>Hatred,</hi> or at leaſt from <hi>a want of charity.</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Aſc. <hi>B. Mar.</hi> Serm. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> Quiſque (ſaith St. <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi>) ſibi unus debet eſſe per integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem virtutis, &amp; unum cum proximis per vinculum dilectionis. <hi>Every one ought to be one with himſelf by the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity of Vertue, and one with his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour by the bond of Charity.</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Bapt. con <hi>Don.</hi> l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> Love u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites, but hatred divides, and breaks out into Schiſm. <hi>Nulli</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi>) <hi>Schiſma facerent, ſi fraterno odio non excaecarentur. None would make Schiſms, unleſs they were blinded with the hatred of their Brethren.</hi> This Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter was evident in the <hi>Donatiſts;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Contra</hi> Creſc. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 10.</note> hence the ſame Father tells them, <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramenta habetis, charitatem non habet is, Sacraments you have, but Charity you have not.</hi> And withal, he tells them, that though they had, <hi>multa &amp; magna,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Bapt. cont. <hi>Don.</hi> l <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>8, 9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>many and great things,</hi> yet all was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, <hi>ſi unum defuerit, if that one thing Charity were wanting;</hi> and what Charity they could have who allowed no Church but their own, I know not. When there are no juſt Scruples, no reaſonable Cauſes of Separation,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:60567:24"/>ſurely the departure muſt be for want of Charity.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3dly.</hi> Schiſmatical Separation iſſues out of <hi>Pride and Contempt.</hi> When they went out from the Apoſtolical Church, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.19. there was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of Antichriſtian Pride and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt in it; for in the verſe precedent, <hi>Antichriſts</hi> are ſaid to be then in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Thoſe that <hi>ſeparated themſelves</hi> Jud. 19. did it, as a Learned man ſaith, <hi>cum contemptu aliorum,</hi> as if they had ſome peculiar Doctrine or Sanctity. This Character may be ſeen in the <hi>Novatians</hi> and <hi>Donatiſts. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatus</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>Superbiâ inflatus, puft up with pride,</hi> when he ſet up his Separate Church, that he might be head of thoſe who called themſelves pure.<note place="margin">Euſeb. <hi>l</hi> 6. <hi>cap</hi> 42.</note> The <hi>Roman</hi> Synod takes notice of this, and decreed, That he, <hi>cum ſimul elatis, with his proud companions,</hi> ſhould be eſteemed as Aliens to that Church. St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith of the <hi>Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts,</hi> that <hi>Superbi ruperunt rete &amp; fecere altare contra altare. Proud men broke the net, and ſet up Altar againſt Altar.</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:60567:24"/>It was indeed horrible pride in them to ſay, that the Church was <hi>only in parte Donati;</hi> and it is no leſs in the Papiſts to ſay, that it is <hi>only in parte Papae.</hi> For any one Party to boaſt, as if the Church were with them <hi>on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> and not elſewhere, is Schiſmatical Pride, or proud Schiſm. Then is Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration a Schiſm, when it is done in pride and contempt.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4thly.</hi> Schiſmatical Separation is ordinarily, if not always, <hi>attended with ſome error or other,</hi> It is a very are thing to ſee a <hi>mere ſimple Schiſm, ſine ullâ depravatâ Doctrinâ, without ſome mixture of depraved Doctrine.</hi> Every <hi>Zimri</hi> hath its <hi>Cosby;</hi> every Divider hath ſome lie or other to which he is joined. <hi>Neque Schiſma feri poteſt, niſi diverſum aliquid ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quantur qui faciunt,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Auſtin.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cont.</hi> Creſ. <hi>l</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>Neither can there be a Schiſm made, unleſs they that make it follow ſome dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Doctrine.</hi> Nullum Schiſma non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bi aliquam fingit Haereſin ut recte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>b Eccleſia receſſiſſe videatur,<note place="margin">Com. in <hi>Tit.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſaith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t.</hi> Jerome; <hi>There is no Schiſm but it
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:60567:25"/>frames to it ſelf ſome Hereſy, that it may ſeem to have rightly departed from the Church. Novatus</hi> did not only ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from the Church, but ſet up his own Error, <hi>That the lapſed were not to be received in the Church,</hi> no, not upon their repentance, no more than dead men. <hi>Donatus</hi> did not <hi>merely</hi> ſeparate, but advanced his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable Error, That the Church was <hi>only in parte Donati;</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Unit. Eccl. c. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> upon which account St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> tells him, that he did, <hi>aliud Evangelizare, preach ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Goſpel.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theod. <hi>Hiſt. l.</hi> 3, 5.</note> Neither did the <hi>Luciferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ani</hi> only ſeparate, but they had their <hi>propria Dogmata, their proper Errors.</hi> Thus the Learned <hi>Whitaker,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Notis Eccl. Q. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Non eſt Schiſma niſi cum Errore aliquo conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum fuerit. There is no Schiſm, but it is in conjunction with ſome Error.</hi> The Schiſmatick ever hath ſome peculiar Opinion to promote in the world, and upon that account he ſeparates from the Church, and ſets up for himſelf.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5thly.</hi> Schiſmatical Separation is a breach of ſome <hi>Sacred <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</hi> The Schiſmatick doth indeed <hi>adhere to the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:60567:25"/>Church in part,</hi> but with all he <hi>breaks in part.</hi> There is ſome breach of Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. He <hi>adheres to the Church in part,</hi> but not in all. St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith of the <hi>Donatiſts, In multis erant mecum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Enarr. in <hi>Pſal. 54.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>in Schiſmate non mecum. In many things they are with me, but in their Schiſm they are not with me.</hi> And in another place he ſaith, That they were <hi>with the Church in Sacraments, but not</hi> in vinculo pacis, <hi>in the bond of peace.</hi> Thus the Schiſmatick adheres in part, but then <hi>he breaks in part:</hi> There is ſome breach of <hi>ſacred <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> I mean of that Unity that is founded in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Hence St.<note place="margin">De Unit. Eccl.</note> 
               <hi>Cyprian</hi> expoſtulates with the Schiſmaticks, <hi>Quis audeat ſcindere unitatem Dei, veſtem Domini, Eccleſiam Chriſti? Who dares break the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of God, the ſeamleſs Coat of the Lord, the Church of Chriſt?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Contra.</hi> Parm. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 1, 11.</note> Hence St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> tells them, <hi>Non eſt quicquam gravius Sacrilegio Schiſmatis; There is nothing more grievous than the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Schiſm.</hi> Were there no breach of Unity, it would not be Schiſm; were not the Unity <hi>ſacred,</hi> it would not be <hi>Sacriledge.</hi> Then is Separation
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:60567:26"/>Schiſm when there is a breach of ſome <hi>ſacred <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6thly,</hi> Schiſmatical Separation is a breach of Sacred Unity, <hi>for little or no cauſe at all.</hi> The memorable Mr.<note place="margin">Tract of Schiſm.</note> 
               <hi>Hale</hi>'s ſpeaking about the Schiſm touching the keeping of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> ſaith, <hi>This matter tho moſt unneceſſary, moſt vain, yet cauſed as great a Combuſtion, as ever was in the Church; the</hi> Weſt <hi>ſeparating and refuſing Communion with the</hi> Eaſt <hi>for many years together. In this fantaſtical Hurry, I cannot ſee but all the World were Schiſmaticks, neither can any thing excuſe them from that imputation, excepting only this that we charitably ſuppoſe all Partie out of Conſcience did what they did.</hi> Thus he. This great Schiſm was for juſt little or nothing, and ſo is every Schiſm, that is properly ſo called The Separation is as the <hi>cauſe</hi> is When the cauſe is weighty and juſt the Separation is innocent. When the Cauſe is light and inconſiderable the Separation is Schiſm. Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks are but <hi>tanquam paleae, as chaff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:60567:26"/>and as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeaks,<note place="margin">Expoſ. in Epiſt. <hi>Joh.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Occaſione ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti volant foras: A little Wind drives them out of doors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7thly,</hi> Schiſmatical Separation is not only from a particular Church, but <hi>from the Catholick one.</hi> As by a juſt Excommunication a Man is caſt out from the Church <hi>Catholick,</hi> ſo by an unjuſt Separation a man caſts out himſelf from the ſame. The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Primate <hi>Bramhall</hi> in his <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of the Church of</hi> England, lays down two things; the one is this, <hi>If one Part of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church ſeparate it ſelf from another, not abſolutely, or in eſſentials, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively in Abuſes and Innovations; not as it is a part of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church, but only ſo far as it is corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and degenerated, it doth ſtill retain a Communion not only with the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church, but even with that cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted Church from which it is ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, except only in Corruptions.</hi> The other is this, <hi>Whoſoever ſeparates himſelf from any part of the Catholick Church, as it is a part of the Catholick
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:60567:27"/>Church, doth ſeparate himſelf from every part of the Catholick Church, and conſequently from the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church, which hath no Exiſtence but in its Parts.</hi> Thus that Learned Man. It is one thing to ſeparate from a Particular Church as it is corrupted and dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated; another thing to ſeparate from a Particular Church, as it is a part of the Catholick Church. The Learned Dr. <hi>Prideaux</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">De Viſib. Eccleſ.</note> 
               <hi>Non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendus eſt Schiſmaticus, qui Romam aut aliam quamvis deſerit particularem Eccleſiam, ob additamenta non ſerenda; ſed qui averſatur Communionem &amp; u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatem Eccleſiae <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſalis &amp; Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licae. He is not to be eſteemed a Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick, who forſakes</hi> Rome, <hi>or any other Particular Church, becauſe of ſome Additions not to be born; but he that turns away from the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion and Communion of the Church Catholick and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. ad <hi>Cornel.</hi> l. <hi>2.</hi> Ep. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> St. <hi>Cypriam</hi> charges it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Novatians,</hi> that they did, <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicae Eccleſiae corpus unum ſcindere: Cut in pieces that one Body of the Church Catholick.</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Unit. Eccl. c. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> charges it upon the <hi>Donatiſts, A Chriſtianâ
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:60567:27"/>unitate, quae toto orbe diffunditur, ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lego ſchiſmate ſeparatos eſſe: That they were by a Sacrilegious Schiſm ſeparated from that Chriſtian <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, which is diffuſed over the whole world.</hi> Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is then Schiſm, when it is from a particular Church, <hi>as it is a part of the Church Catholick;</hi> for then it is from every part of the Catholick Church, and by conſequence from the whole Church.</p>
            <p>Theſe Characters may ſuffice to ſhew what Separation <hi>amounts to Schiſm.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:60567:28"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> 
            </head>
            <argument>
               <p>The Separation of the N. C. is not Schiſm. Not voluntary. Not from want of Charity. Not from Pride and Contempt. Not attended with Error. No breach of Sacred <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity. Not for little or no Cauſe. The Rites and Ceremonies for which they ſeparate no little things, as conſidered in themſelves. Of the Sign of the Croſs in Baptiſm. The Ceremonies, as terms of Communion, intrench on Chriſt's Kingly Office: Invert the Goſpel; are againſt Chriſtian Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Liberty and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity. The Pleas for Ceremonies not ſatisfactory. Of Order and Decency. Whether the Ceremonies are parts of Worſhip. N. C. do not ſeparate from the Catholick Church.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>I Now go on to conſider the Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the <hi>Nonconformiſts,</hi> Miniſters and People, whether that be Schiſm or not; in the doing of which I ſhall review the former Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters with reſpect to them.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:60567:28"/>
               <hi>1ſt.</hi> Schiſmatical Separation is <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentional</hi> and <hi>perfectly voluntary;</hi> but <hi>quo animo,</hi> do the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> ſeparate? In our Law an <hi>entry</hi> ſhall not be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a <hi>diſſeiſin,</hi> partibus invitis, <hi>againſt the will of the Agents.</hi> Neither ſhould a Separation in ſuch a Caſe be in The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ology called a <hi>Schiſm.</hi> Is it imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that the <hi>intention</hi> or <hi>option</hi> of the Nonconformiſts ſhould be to be out of the Church, rather than in it? It is eaſy to judge who they be that moſt intend and love Church-unity; thoſe who would have the <hi>terms</hi> of it <hi>eaſy, plain and unqueſtionable,</hi> or thoſe who would have them clogg'd <hi>with Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</hi> The Nonconformiſts ſeparate; but their parting from the Church, like the Merchant's parting with his Goods in a Storm, is not <hi>purely volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary,</hi> but a <hi>mixt Action,</hi> done with an unwilling will, not out of love to Separation, but to ſalve Conſcience. When the Papiſts charge Schiſm upon our Church, what ſaith Biſhop <hi>Bram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reply to the Biſhop of <hi>Chalced.</hi> fol. 55.</note> Schiſm is a <hi>voluntary</hi> Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; <hi>To be ſeparated might be our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent will, becauſe we could not help
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:60567:29"/>it: but it was far enough from our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent will, or that we did deſire it.</hi> And a little after. <hi>If they did impoſe upon us a neceſſity of doing ſinful things, and offending God, and wounding our Conſciences, then we did not leave them, but they did drive us from them.</hi> And what ſaith Dr. <hi>Prideaux, Fugati po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius quam fugientes, non tam à</hi> Roma <hi>ut eſt ſeceſſimus, quàm ad</hi> Roman <hi>ut erat, regreſſi ſumus, We were rather dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven away, than voluntarily flying; we are not ſo much departed from</hi> Rome <hi>as it is, as we are returned to</hi> Rome <hi>as it was.</hi> In like manner, the Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts being charged with Schiſm, may ſay, To ſeparate is <hi>not their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent will, but Conſequent;</hi> they depart from the Church, but it is by a kind of <hi>conſtraint;</hi> they had <hi>much rather</hi> be in the Church; they <hi>wiſh for</hi> it, <hi>pray for</hi> it, and <hi>ſalvâ conſcientiâ,</hi> would do any thing for it, but there are ſome things which they cannot join in: Such a departure ſhould not be called Schiſm.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:60567:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> Schiſmatical Separation pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from <hi>hatred,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Schiſmatici diſceſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus iniquis à fraternâ Charitate diſſiliunt. <hi>Aug.</hi> de Fide, &amp; Symbol. cap. 10.</note> or at <hi>leaſt</hi> from a <hi>want of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> but do the Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts <hi>thus</hi> ſeparate? What is done out of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to God,</hi> cannot be fairly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted <hi>hatred to our Brother.</hi> It is love to God that cauſes men to walk according to Conſcience; but it is want of love to him that makes them hate their Brother. Theſe two can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtand together. If we call that hatred which indeed is Conſcience, we forfeit our own Charity by miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtruing the Charity of others. It is the deſire of the Nonconformiſts to live in charity with the Conforming Brethren. In the Council of <hi>Carthage</hi> St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> and his Fellow-Biſhops, in the point of rebaptizing thoſe that were baptized by Hereticks, plainly erred and diſſented from the reſt of the Church; yet they were never charged with <hi>Schiſm</hi> for it, and why? Becauſe they did it <hi>neminem judicantes, neo à jure communionis aliquem, ſi diverſum ſenſerit, amoventes: Judging none,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:60567:30"/>removing none, that thought otherwiſe, from the right of Communion.</hi> That Error of Rebaptization,<note place="margin">De Bapt. cont. <hi>Don.</hi> l. <hi>1.</hi> c. ult.</note> which in the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> was, as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Fuligo in tartareâ faeditate, the ſmoak of their helliſh filthineſs,</hi> was in St. <hi>Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> but, <hi>naevus in candore ſanctae Animae, a freckle in the candor of an holy Soul;</hi> and the reaſon was, becauſe St. <hi>Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> had what they had not, <hi>Charitatis ubera, the breaſts of Charity</hi> to cover his Defects. In reſpect of this Charity Biſhop <hi>Davenant</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Sentent. de Pace <hi>112.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Melius de Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiâ meruit errans</hi> Cyprianus, <hi>quam</hi> Stephanus Romanus <hi>recte ſentiens, &amp; Eccleſias quantum in ſe fuit, Schiſmatico Spiritu dilacerans.</hi> Cyprian, <hi>erring, deſerved better of the Church, than</hi> Stephen, <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Rome, <hi>rightly thinking, but by a Schiſmatical Spirit, as much as he could renting the Churches.</hi> Charity is a great thing, and I hope it may be found among the Nonconformiſts; they leave the Church, <hi>neminem judicantes, judging none</hi> of their Conforming Brethren <hi>the breaſts of their Charity</hi> may cover ſome defects. I hope therefore Schiſm
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:60567:30"/>in this reſpect cannot be charged upon them. I am ſure Charity is in all good men, Conforming or Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming; but if we compare <hi>Parties</hi> together, that Party which <hi>binds bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens on Conſcience, and leaves them there,</hi> ſeems to me to have leſs of Charity, than that which ſhrinks and withdraws the Shoulder from them.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3dly.</hi> Schiſmatical Separation iſſues out of <hi>pride and contempt.</hi> The <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſts</hi> thought themſelves the <hi>only</hi> men; they boaſted as if their Communion were the <hi>only</hi> Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,<note place="margin">Si noſtra communio eſt Eccleſia, veſtra non eſt. <hi>Aug.</hi> de Bapt. cont. <hi>Don.</hi> l. 1. c. 11.</note> as if their Baptiſm were the <hi>only</hi> Baptiſm.<note place="margin">Vos dicitis in nobis Baptiſmum non eſſe. <hi>Auſt.</hi> contr. <hi>Creſc.</hi> l. 4. cap. 62.</note> But do the Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts ſeparate <hi>thus?</hi> Do they ſay that <hi>they only</hi> are the Church, or that <hi>they only</hi> have the Ordinances? Do they deſpiſe their Conforming Brethren, or lift up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves above them? No ſurely, they deſire to be but as Brethren, and that one Brother might not <hi>Lord it over</hi> another. When our Divines charge
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:60567:31"/>the Monaſteries as Schiſmatical, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have ſeparate Meetings and Ordinances, <hi>Bellarmin</hi> anſwers thus.<note place="margin">De Not. Eccl. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Soli Schiſmatici ſunt qui ita erigunt altare proprium, ut altare alio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum prophanum cenſeant. They only are Schiſmaticks, who ſo ſet up their own Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, that they eſteem the Altar of others prophane.</hi> It is indeed one thing to have <hi>diſtinct</hi> Meetings for Worſhip, and another to have <hi>oppoſite</hi> ones. The Nonconformiſts have Meetings of their own, but without the contempt of others. The <hi>Jews</hi> ſay, he that contemns the Solemn Aſſemblies of the Church, hath no part in <hi>Seculo futuro.</hi> But where the diſtinct Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings are <hi>without contempt,</hi> there, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it is not to be called Schiſm. Here that may take place; <hi>he that is not againſt the Church, is for it.</hi> A candid Charity interprets all to the beſt.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4thly.</hi> Schiſmatical Separation is ordinarily, if not always, attended with ſome <hi>Error or other.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Schiſma in Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſim eru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctat.</note> The <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatians, Donatiſts, Luciferians,</hi> had their <hi>propria Dogmata,</hi> their <hi>proper
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:60567:31"/>Errors.</hi> Their Separations were to ſet up their Errors; their Errors un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of Truth, were to juſtify their Separations. Hence St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith, that the Schiſmaticks are,<note place="margin">De Unit. Eccl.</note> 
               <hi>Peſtes &amp; lues Fidei, corrumpendae veritatis artifices, the Peſts and Plagues of the Faith, the Artiſts in corrupting Truth.</hi> But as for the Nonconformiſts, what <hi>new Doctrine</hi> do they bring? what <hi>Error</hi> do they propagate? what deadly poiſon is under their Lips? Do they not fully and firmly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to the Church (as <hi>Optatus</hi> ſpeaks) <hi>in una Fide, in one Faith?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Whit.</hi> de Not Eccl. cap. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> are they not joined together, <hi>ut in manu digiti, as the fingers in the hand</hi> pointing out the ſame pure Doctrine? Biſhop <hi>Abbot,</hi> in his Book <hi>De gratiâ &amp; perſeverantiâ,</hi> tells us of ſome Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupters,<note place="margin">Praſat. ad Lect.</note> 
               <hi>Qui veteres haereſes denuo in Scenam producunt, &amp; Pelagianâ lue correpti Gratiae Divinae vim nervoſque ſuccidunt, Who bring up the old Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies upon the ſtage, and having caught the Pelagian Peſtilence, cut aſunder the ſtrength and nerves of Divine Grace.</hi> Not only ſome of our men, but Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:60567:32"/>too, have taken notice that the Plague of <hi>Socinianiſm</hi> hath been creeping in among us.<note place="margin">Upon the 8th Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle.</note> Mr. <hi>Rogers</hi> upon the <hi>Articles of our Church</hi> tells us, that he heard a great Learned man ſpeaking of <hi>Zanchy</hi>'s Book, <hi>De tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Elohim,</hi> call him <hi>a Fool and an Aſs. Arnoldus,</hi> in his Book againſt the <hi>Racovian Catechiſm,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Praef. ad Lect.</note> takes notice of the <hi>Socinian</hi> Hereſy creeping up among us. But do the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> propagate theſe Errors? Do they ſpread abroad the poiſon? Do they not ſteddily ſtick to the true pure Doctrine of our Church? And is not <hi>conformity in Doctrine</hi> much more than <hi>conformity in Ceremonies?</hi> Surely it is. It ſeems therefore hard to charge Schiſm upon them. He indeed goes out of the Church, who goes out, not in Body, but in Faith. Hence it was the judgment of <hi>Gerſom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ger.</hi> de Eccleſ. cap. <hi>6.</hi> ſect. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> That in a ſimple Schiſm, without any depraved Doctrine added to it, when it is doubtful by whom the Schiſm is made, till it be lawfully determined, thoſe that are Followers in it do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the Church.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:60567:32"/>
               <hi>5thly.</hi> Schiſmatical Separation is a breach of ſome <hi>Sacred <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</hi> The Schiſmatick <hi>adheres to the Church in part,</hi> but withal he <hi>breaks in part.</hi> He <hi>adheres in part,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Bapt. cont. <hi>Don.</hi> l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> or elſe he would be an <hi>Apoſtate.</hi> Thus St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith of the <hi>Donatiſts, In quo nobiſcum ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiunt, in co nobiſcum ſunt, In what they think with us, in that they are with us.</hi> Thus when the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> asked whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their Baptiſm did generate Sons to God; <hi>If it did not generate, why doth not the Catholick Church rebaptize them; but if it do generate, then ours</hi> (ſay the <hi>Donatiſts) is the Church.</hi> St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> makes this anſwer,<note place="margin">De Bapt. cont. <hi>Don.</hi> l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> That the Church of the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> doth generate, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde conjuncta eſt, non unde Separata eſt. Separata eſt à vinculo, Charitatis, ſed adjuncta eſt in uno Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmate. It generates as it is joined to the Church Catholick, not as it is ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from it. It is ſeparated from the bond of Charity, but it is joined in one Baptiſm.</hi> Thus the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oined to the Church in part. Again, The Schiſmatick, though he adhere to the Church in part, yet withal
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:60567:33"/>
               <hi>he breaks in part,</hi> or elſe he could be no Schiſmatick. Thus St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith of the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Bapt. contr. <hi>Don.</hi> l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>In eo à nobis receſſerunt, in quo à nobis diſſentiunt, In that they are departed from us in which they diſſent from us.</hi> When <hi>Creſconius</hi> urged for the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> that there was, <hi>una Religio, eadem Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta, nihil in Chriſtianâ obſervatione diverſum;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Contra <hi>Creſc.</hi> l. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That on both ſides there was the ſame Religion, the ſame Sacraments, nothing in Chriſtian obſervation diverſe.</hi> (Which Plea by the way, had it been true, would have been good, there being no Schiſm where there is no breach of Unity.) St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> utterly denies it, and asks them, <hi>Quare re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptizatis? Why do you rebaptize</hi> thoſe that were baptized in the Catholick Church? Indeed they thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the <hi>only</hi> Church, and ſo broke themſelves off from the Church Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick. Thus the Schiſmatick is partly in conjunction with the Church, and partly in ſeparation from it; he adheres in one thing, and breaks off in another. But is it thus with the Nonconformiſts? Are not
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:60567:33"/>they joined to the Church in all that which is <hi>truly <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity?</hi> Have not they in their Meetings the <hi>unity</hi> of <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances,</hi> the ſame pure <hi>Word</hi> preached, the ſame holy <hi>Sacraments</hi> adminiſtred, and this by <hi>true Miniſters of Chriſt?</hi> And what other Unity is there in Viſible Churches? Or what of true Unity is there between two Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochial Churches, which is not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween their Meetings and Parochial Churches? Abate but <hi>Humane things,</hi> in which <hi>Church unity ſtands not,</hi> and they are not partially, but <hi>totally in conjunction with the Church of</hi> England; and if ſo, there is no breach of Unity, and by conſequence <hi>no Schiſm</hi> in them.<note place="margin">De Bapt. cont. <hi>Don.</hi> l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> lays down a notable Rule; That he that acts, <hi>Sicut in unitate agitur, as it is done in the unity;</hi> in eo manet atque conjungitur, <hi>in that he abides, and is joined, in all thoſe things wherein <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity ſtands.</hi> The Nonconformiſts act as the Church doth, therefore they are in conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with it. St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> tells us,<note place="margin">Contra <hi>Creſc.</hi> l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> That the Church doth in the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, <hi>Omnia quae ſua ſunt, all
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:60567:34"/>things that are its own.</hi> Let the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming Miniſters acknowledge all that of true Unity which is in the Diſſenters Meetings, and they may perceive that their Brethren are in conjunction with them. Where there is a total conjunction, there is no breach of true Unity; and where there is no ſuch breach, there is no Schiſm. But you will ſay, their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture from the Congregations in publick, is a Schiſm. I anſwer, Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>local</hi> Separation is not a Schiſm there is more in Schiſm than ſo. Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry departure is not Schiſm. It is hardly to be called ſuch, when thoſe that depart do yet remain in conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with them from whom they depart. And this I think is the Caſe of thoſe that are Nonconformiſts.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6thly.</hi> Schiſmatical Separation is a breach of ſacred Unity <hi>for little or no cauſe at all.</hi> Hence <hi>Irenaeus</hi> ſaith o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Schiſmaticks, That <hi>propter modi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas &amp; quaſlibet cauſas, magnum &amp; glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſum Corpus Chriſti conſcindunt, for little and inconſiderable Cauſes they cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:60567:34"/>in pieces the great and glorious Body of Chriſt.</hi> The Profeſſors of <hi>Leyden</hi> ſay,<note place="margin">Synopſ. pur. Theol. Diſp. <hi>40.</hi>
               </note> That a Schiſmatical Church is that, <hi>quae propter externos aliquos ritus,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Communionem Chriſtianam ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumpit, which for ſome external indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Rites breaks Chriſtian Communion.</hi> This Character ſeems <hi>prima facie</hi> to preſs upon the Separation of the Nonconformiſts. They ſeparate for <hi>Rites and Ceremonies,</hi> which ſeem to be but minute and inconſiderable things; this therefore muſt be duly conſidered.</p>
            <p>The Ceremonies of our Church may be conſidered under a double notion; either as they are in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or elſe as they are terms of Communion.</p>
            <p>The Ceremonies, as conſidered <hi>in themſelves,</hi> however innocent they ſeem to be to the Conformiſts, they are not ſo to the Nonconformiſts. To inſtance but in one of them. The <hi>Croſs in Baptiſm</hi> is lookt upon as a thing unlawful, or at leaſt as a thing very ill-coloured, and ſuſpected to be unlawful. To explain this I ſhall lay down ſome few things.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:60567:35"/>
               <hi>1ſt.</hi> The Sign of the Croſs was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed uſed among the Ancient Fathers, but not without <hi>a mixture of Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Cor. Mil.</note> 
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> will have <hi>Signaculum Crucis</hi> to be neceſſary in <hi>every part of our life.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> adv. <hi>Judaeos.</hi>
               </note> St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith, That <hi>in hoc Signo Crucis ſalus ſit omnibus qui in frontibus notentur, in this Sign of the Croſs there is Salvation to all who have this mark in their Foreheads. Origen</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">In <hi>Exod.</hi> cap. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> That <hi>fear and trembling falls up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Devils,</hi> cum Signum Crucis in nobis viderint, <hi>when they ſee the Sign of the Croſs in us.</hi> St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Ser. <hi>43.</hi>
               </note> That <hi>all proſperity is</hi> in uno Signo Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti, <hi>in that one sign of Chriſt; he that ſows in it, ſhall have a Crop of Eternal Life; he that jour mes in it, ſhall arrive at Heaven it ſelf.</hi> St. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> ſaith, <hi>That</hi> Signo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> racis omnia magica com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſcuntur,<note place="margin">De Incar. verbi.</note> 
               <hi>all Conjurations are repreſſed by the Sign of the Croſs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">In <hi>Matt.</hi> Homil. <hi>55.</hi>
               </note> St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſaith, That <hi>all Sacraments are perfected</hi> Signo Crucis, <hi>with the Sign of the Croſs.</hi> St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">In <hi>Joh.</hi> Tract. <hi>118.</hi>
               </note> That <hi>unleſs the Sign of the Croſs be applied to the Forehead of the Believers, or to the Water of Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, or to the Oyl with which they
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:60567:35"/>are anointed, or to the Sacrifice with which they are nouriſhed,</hi> nihil eorum rite perficitur, <hi>none of theſe things are rightly performed.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellarm.</hi> de Imag. lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> Such a uſe of the Croſs as this is, Proteſtants cannot allow of. Only the Papiſts, who would have Humane Inventions do great things, make uſe of ſuch Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in the Fathers.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2dly.</hi> The Sign of the Croſs is <hi>an abominable Idol in the Popiſh Church. Bellarmine</hi> (who doth diſtinguiſh the Croſs into three parts, the True Croſs, the Image of the Croſs, and the Sign of the Croſs) lays down this general Doctrine. <hi>Omnes Cruces adoramus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bell.</hi> l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>30.</hi> de Imag.</note> 
               <hi>We worſhip all Croſſes:</hi> And particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly of the <hi>Sign</hi> of the Croſs he ſaith, That it is, <hi>Signum ſacrum &amp; venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile, a ſacred and venerable Sign. Aquinas</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Pars <hi>3.</hi> Q. <hi>25.</hi> Art. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> That <hi>the Image of Chriſt is to be adored,</hi> cultu latriae, <hi>the Sign is to have the ſame adoration as the thing it ſelf.</hi> And how? which way is it that ſuch an horrible Idol ſhould be retained in a Church Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, and pure from Idolatry? The
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:60567:36"/>Brazen Serpent was ordained by God himſelf, and yet when it was abuſed to Idolatry, <hi>Hezekiah</hi> broke it to pieces, and called it <hi>Nehuſhtan, a piece of braſs,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.4. It was a ſingular Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of Chriſt. The lifting of it up upon a pole for corporal Cures, did by <hi>Divine</hi> Ordination type out the lifting up of him upon the Croſs for ſpiritual; yet becoming an Idol, it was no more to be endured: And why ſhould the Croſs, <hi>a mere Human Invention,</hi> being once ſo abuſed, ever be tolerated? The Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Hoſ. 2.16, 17. were not to mention <hi>the names of Idols,</hi> that is, honoris gratiâ, <hi>in any way for their honour.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Crab.</hi> Conc. Tom. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> The Fifth Council of <hi>Carthage,</hi> Can. 15. would have all Idolatrous Reliques utterly extinguiſhed. <hi>Conſtantine the Great</hi> would not ſuffer the leaſt Rag or Memorial of Pagan Idolatry to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main: And it is very ſtrange,<note place="margin">Euſeb. <hi>Vit.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant. <hi>l.</hi> 3.47, <hi>&amp;</hi> 52.</note> that ſuch an Idold as the Croſs ſhould be retained in a Church free from Idolatry.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:60567:36"/>
               <hi>3dly.</hi> The Sign of the Croſs in our own Church, though it be no Idol, yet is an Image; it is not indeed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a <hi>graven Image,</hi> but it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a <hi>ſimilitude of Chriſt</hi> crucified. <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation</hi> is the very eſſence of an Image; and the Sign of the Croſs is intended to <hi>reſemble</hi> Chriſt crucified.<note place="margin">Aquin. <hi>Pars</hi> 3. <hi>Q.</hi> 83. <hi>Art.</hi> 1.</note> As the Sacraments are by God's In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution repreſentative Images of Chriſt's Paſſion, ſo is the Croſs by Man's; and what doth an <hi>Image</hi> do in Divine Worſhip? The Second Commandment ſhuts out all <hi>Images</hi> from it; nay, under that notion, it would ſhut out the very Sacraments, were they not of Divine Ordination. Anciently the Chriſtians would not ſuffer Images to be in their Churches.<note place="margin">Ael. Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prid. <hi>in vita</hi> Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andri.</note> When the Emperor <hi>Adrian</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded Temples to be made <hi>without Images,</hi> it was preſently conceived hat he did prepare them for <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conc.</hi> El. <hi>Can.</hi> 36. Epiph. <hi>Epiſt. ad</hi> Joh. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſol.</note> The <hi>Eliberine</hi> Council would not admit that <hi>Pictures</hi> ſhould be in Churches. <hi>Epiphanius</hi> rent the Vail that hung in the Church of <hi>Anablatha,</hi> becauſe it had the <hi>Image of Chriſt,</hi> or
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:60567:37"/>ſome Saint in it. <hi>Serenus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Marſiles,</hi> brake down the <hi>Images</hi> in his Church. The Emperor <hi>Theodoſius</hi> and <hi>Valentinian</hi> removed, <hi>quodcunque Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Salvatoris, every Sign of a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour out of the way.</hi> Thus Images have not been admitted into <hi>Churches;</hi> and how then ſhould they be brought into <hi>Ordinances,</hi> which are much more ſacred than Places? The Image of the Croſs ſhould not appear in Divine Worſhip, in which no other Image is to be admitted, but that,<note place="margin">Auſt. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 119. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>quae ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eſt quod Deus eſt, which is that which God is;</hi> that is, Jeſus Chriſt the Image of the Inviſible God.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4thly.</hi> The Sign of the Croſs is an addition to Baptiſm, and ſo utterly unwarrantable. Under the <hi>Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament</hi> it was unlawful to add to the Ceremonial Law of God, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.2. And how ſhould it be lawful under the <hi>New</hi> to add to the Ceremonial Law of Chriſt? Chriſt was as faithful in the Houſe of God as <hi>Moſes;</hi> his proviſion was as perfect for Rituals, as that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> was. Nay, the Worſhip under
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:60567:37"/>the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> being more Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowy and Ritual, and that under the <hi>New</hi> more pure and ſimple; an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to this is leſs tolerable than to that, becauſe the purer the Worſhip is, the more impure is the addition. The Prophet <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> ſpeaking of the Glory of the Evangelical Church, that it was the place of God's <hi>Throne, and of the ſoles of his feet;</hi> adds this, That they ſhould no more <hi>ſet their threſholds by God's, or their poſts by his, Ezek.</hi> 43.7, &amp; 8. they ſhould not add their own Inventions to God's Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts. When the <hi>Corinthians</hi> joined, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, their <hi>own ſupper</hi> to the Lord's, it was unjuſtifiable; and the Apoſtle expoſtulates about it, <hi>Have ye not houſes to eat and to drink in? or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe ye the Church of God?</hi> 1 Cor. 11.22. Are there not diſtinct Houſes, and diſtinct Suppers? why do you join the Civil Supper to the Sacred? The Apoſtle againſt ſuch mixtures alledgeth that Inſtitution,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Parker</hi> of the Crols. 102.</note> 
               <hi>I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of the Lord that which I deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto you,</hi> v. 23. Man may not add to what is from God. When the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:60567:38"/>
               <hi>Armenians</hi> added <hi>ſod meat</hi> to the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> it was condemned by a General Council. When the <hi>Artoty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritae</hi> brought in their <hi>bread and cheeſe</hi> into it,<note place="margin">Epiph. <hi>Hereſ.</hi> 49.</note> it was abominable; when they brought in their <hi>mulſum or melli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi> into it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Concil</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſidor. <hi>Can.</hi> 8.</note> the Church calls it, <hi>aliud poculum, another cup;</hi> and that, <hi>ad grande peccatum &amp; reatum pertinet, it amounts to a great ſin and guilt, as being an addition to Chriſt's Inſtitution.</hi> It's true, the Fathers in this Council did through infirmity admit, <hi>Vinum cum aquâ mixtum, a mixture of Water with Wine;</hi> but another Council will not admit, no not of a <hi>little water</hi> mixt with the Wine, and adds this reaſon for it;<note place="margin">Crab. <hi>Tom.</hi> 2. Aurelia. 4. <hi>Can.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>Quia Sacrilegium judicatur aliud offerri, quam quod in Mandatis Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſimis Salvator inſtituit. Becauſe it is judged Sacriledge to offer any thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that which our Saviour inſtituted in his Sacred Commands.</hi> When <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raeus</hi> cites many Fathers for the many Ceremonies added to Baptiſm, the Anſwer of the Learned <hi>Whitaker</hi> is very excellent.<note place="margin">Whit. <hi>Tom.</hi> 1. 191, 192.</note> 
               <hi>Meâ non intereſt qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Clemens, <hi>quid</hi> Leo, <hi>quid</hi> Damaſus
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:60567:38"/>
               <hi>quid quiſquam alius Pontifex ad Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi Sacramentum adjecerit; Chriſtus Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae nihil de iſtis Ceremoniarum nugis mandavit. I am not concerned what</hi> Clemens, Leo, Damaſus, <hi>or any other Pope hath added to the Sacrament of Baptiſm; Chriſt left to his Church no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in command touching ſuch trifling Ceremonies.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sadeel. <hi>Art.</hi> 12. <hi>fol.</hi> 492.</note> 
               <hi>Sadeel</hi> againſt the <hi>Monks of Burdeaux,</hi> ſpeaking touching their many Ceremonies added to Baptiſm as an ornament to it, makes this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. <hi>Num igitur ſunt prudentiores Jeſu Chriſto, qui inſtituit Baptiſmum tantâ cum ſimplicitate &amp; puritate, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que melius novit, quam omnes ſimul ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines, quae illi conveniant ornamenta? Hominis licet pactionem (inquit</hi> Paulus) <hi>autoritate confirmatam nemo abrogat, aut quid ei ſuper addit. Quae eſt iſta arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantia adjicere inſtitutioni Jeſu Chriſti? Are they wiſer than Jeſus Chriſt, who inſtituted Baptiſm with ſo great ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city and purity, and who knows much better than all men put together what Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments are proper for it? Though it be but a man's Covenant</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Paul) yet if it be confirmed, no man diſannulleth
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:60567:39"/>or addeth thereunto. What arrogance then is it to add to the Inſtitutions of Jeſus Chriſt?</hi> This is charged upon the Croſs, it is an addition to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm; a Sign of Man's added to the Sign of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5thly.</hi> The Sign of the Croſs is not merely an addition to Baptiſm, but it is a <hi>myſtical Teacher,</hi> and looks very like a <hi>Sacrament.</hi> It is a <hi>myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Teacher;</hi> as the Sacraments teach Chriſt crucified by <hi>God</hi>'s Ordination, ſo doth the Croſs by <hi>Man</hi>'s. But is not the Scripture ſufficient, and Chriſt the great Prophet? And may Man invent new ways of teaching; or if he do, may any one look for the illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minating Spirit in ſuch ways? Chriſt is the one Maſter, the one Teacher by way of excellency; all other Teachers that teach truly, do but teach miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rially under him;<note place="margin">Chriſtus habet cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vem ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellentiae, Alii tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vem Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterii.</note> he hath ordained the perfect means of teaching the Church, and all other means are as none at all. The Croſs not teaching under him, teacheth not truly; and being none of his means, hath none
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:60567:39"/>of his bleſſing. If the <hi>Croſs</hi> might be a true Teacher, then the ſtanding <hi>Images</hi> of Chriſt might be ſo too, which though called by the Papiſts <hi>Lay-mens Books,</hi> do yet but make men forget God. Again, the Sign of the Croſs looks very like a <hi>Sacrament.</hi> Baptiſm is a <hi>Symbol of our Chriſtian Profeſſion,</hi> ſo is the Croſs. Baptiſm hath a <hi>word annexed</hi> to it; <hi>I baptize thee in the name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt.</hi> So hath the Croſs, <hi>We ſign this Child with the Sign of the Croſs, in token that he ſhall not be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to confeſs the faith of Chriſt cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</hi> Baptiſm <hi>points out Chriſt cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,</hi> ſo doth the Croſs. Baptiſm <hi>enters the baptized into the Church,</hi> ſo doth the Croſs. <hi>We receive this Child into the Congregation of Chriſt's flock, and ſign him with the ſign of the Croſs.</hi> As Baptiſm admits into the <hi>Church Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick,</hi> ſo the Croſs admits into a <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church.</hi> Baptiſm <hi>dedicates</hi> the Infant unto Chriſt, ſo the Croſs <hi>dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates</hi> him to the ſervice of him that died on the Croſs.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 30.</note> And what now is wanting to make it a Sacrament? It
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:60567:40"/>is not <hi>vehicalum gratiae;</hi> It's very true, it is not: Neither can <hi>any Human In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention be</hi> ſuch. It therefore looks <hi>as like a Sacrament as any Human thing can do,</hi> no ſuch thing being capable of conveying Grace unto men.</p>
            <p>In the next place the Ceremonies of our Church may be conſidered <hi>as terms of Communion with it:</hi> That is, there muſt be a Surplice, or no preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; a Croſs, or no baptizing; a kneeling poſture, or no Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. Theſe things, though they are very light to the Conformiſts, are not ſo to the Nonconformiſts. I ſhall therefore conſider them in ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1ſt.</hi> The Ceremonies thus taken do ſeem to intrench upon <hi>the Kingly Office of Chriſt.</hi> He is the one Lord and Lawgiver of his Church. 'Tis his Royal Prerogative to inſtitute Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. This is confeſſed by the <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelves.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pars</hi> 3. <hi>Q.</hi> 72. <hi>Art.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Aquinas</hi> (relating that ſome held their Sacrament of Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation was inſtituted in ſome Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:60567:40"/>and that others held it was inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted by the Apoſtles) ſaith, this can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be, becauſe <hi>to inſtitute a new Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament,</hi> pertinet ad poteſtatem ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellentiae, <hi>appertains to the power of excellency,</hi> which is in Chriſt alone.<note place="margin">De Sac. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bellarmin</hi> proves that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Author of Sacraments. It is a flower of his Crown to inſtitute Ordinances, no man may take this glory from him. The Apoſtles, the higheſt Officers in the Church, were not Lords of it, but Miniſters and Stewards under Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1. to do his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. They taught only what he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them, <hi>Matt.</hi> 28.20. St. <hi>Paul</hi> preached <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, nothing without Scripture, <hi>Act.</hi> 26.22. He would not go beyond his Commiſſion.<note place="margin">Tom. <hi>2.</hi> fol. <hi>722.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Non debent Epiſcopi</hi> (ſaith the Excellent <hi>Whitaker) ſuas traditiones aut leges, aut contra, aut extra, aut praeter Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelium obtrudere. The Biſhops ought not to obtrude their Traditions or Laws, either againſt, or without, or beſides the Goſpel. That Goſpel which is the Law of Chriſt, is the Canon that muſt rule all their Canons. Chriſt hath the full Royal
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:60567:41"/>Power, the Church hath only a limited Power from him. Chriſt may make Laws of Inſtitution, the Church can only make Laws of Execution, or Diſpoſition, ſuch as tend to the right and orderly diſpoſing of thoſe. Ordinances which were inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">In legibus Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticis, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, tantum ſpectatur. <hi>Whit.</hi> Tom. 2.721.</note> The Apoſtles did not inſtitute any thing of Worſhip or Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances: But they did take care that the Ordinances ſhould be uſed in a way ſuitable to their dignity. Theſe things being ſo, the only Queſtion is, Whether the Church hath <hi>any Patent or Commiſſion</hi> from Chriſt to inſtitute or impoſe myſtical Ceremonies <hi>as terms of Communion?</hi> In anſwer to this, I take it, the Church hath no ſuch Power or Commiſſion. The Pattern of Chriſt and the Apoſtles is more to me than all the Human Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in the world. It is the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> That Chrſt's. Yoke being eaſy,<note place="margin">Auſt. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 118.</note> he did, <hi>Sacramentis nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mero pauciſſimis, obſervatione facillimis, ſignificatione praeſtantiſſimis ſocietatem novi populi colligare, Tie together the Society of a new People with Sacraments few in number, eaſy in obſervation, and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:60567:41"/>excellent in ſignification:</hi> And who would depart from this ſimplicity? I am ſure the Apoſtles did not. They delivered only that <hi>which they received of the Lord,</hi> 1 Cor 11.23.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De</hi> Or. Err. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>Hoc fidei illorum er at, &amp; officii,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bullinger. This was their faith and duty. They did believe.</hi> (ſaith the ſame Author) <hi>that Chriſt was the wiſdom of God,</hi> ne in mentem ipſorum venit, <hi>it came not into their minds to add Ceremonies to Chriſt's Inſtitutions.</hi> The Primitive Chriſtians continued ſtedfaſtly in the <hi>Apoſtles Doctrine and fellowſhip, and in breaking of bread, and prayer,</hi> Acts 2.42. There was nothing but the pure Inſtitutions of Chriſt, not an additio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Ceremony to be ſeen among them. Nay, in <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi>'s time,<note place="margin">Apol. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> we find the Lord's Supper uſed in pure ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city; and why ſhould we make our additions to the Sacraments? St. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> contra <hi>Aquarios,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. <hi>63.</hi>
               </note> expreſſes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf notably touching the Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. <hi>Ab Evangelicis Praeceptis omnino recedendum non eſt. We muſt not depart from the Evangelical Precepts.</hi> And a little after, <hi>Non niſi Chriſtus ſequendus
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:60567:42"/>eſt, ſolus Chriſtus audiendus eſt. Chriſt only is to be followed, Chriſt alone to be heard.</hi> Again, <hi>Human Ceremonies are not congruous to the pure light of the Goſpel.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tom. <hi>7.</hi> fol. <hi>727.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Num Divinae Figurae ſublatae ſunt, ut Humanae ſuccederent?</hi> ſaith Learned <hi>Whitaker, Were the Divine Figures taken away, that Human might ſucceed?</hi> If the Divine Shadows under the Law did all vaniſh before the Sun, the pure and Evangelical Light; may <hi>Humane <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbra's</hi> come and overcloud it? Surely it cannot be. It was the ſaying of a great Doctor once in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> That <hi>in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Law the ſhadows were larger than the body; and it will be a ſign of the evening and ſun-ſet of Religion, if theſe ſhadows ſhall be ſtretcht out again, and outreach the body.</hi> If the Church may inſtitute or impoſe two or three Ceremonies, it may do more and more; till men under the preſſure cry out,<note place="margin">Epiſt. <hi>119.</hi>
               </note> as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> did, <hi>Tolerabilior ſit conditio Judaeorum, The condition of the Jews would be more tolerable than that of Chriſtians.</hi> Moreover, none but <hi>God alone can inſtitute a Ceremony to
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:60567:42"/>ſignify a myſtery in Religion;</hi> he only hath authority over Religion, he only can bind the Conſcience, he only can illuſtrate the mind, he only can give a bleſſing to ſuch a Sign. <hi>Aquinas,</hi> ſpeaking of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſaith,<note place="margin">Determinare quo Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no ſit utendum pertinet ad ſignificantem, Deus autem eſt qui nobis ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificat Spiritualia per res ſenſibiles in Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, &amp; per verba ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinaria in Scripturis, <hi>Aquin.</hi> part. 3. Qu. 60. Art. 5.</note> That <hi>the Signifier ſhould determine the Sign; and God is the Signifier, who ſignifies ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual things to us by ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible things to us by ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible things, in Sacraments, and by ſimilitudinary words in Scripture.</hi> If God be the great Signifier of Holy Myſteries, it is his right to determine the Signs of them. By theſe things it appears that the Church hath no power to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Myſtical Ceremonies; and by conſequence in ſo doing ſhe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croaches upon the Royal Prerogative of Chriſt.<note place="margin">Walſ. <hi>Hiſt.</hi> 70.</note> 
               <hi>Edward</hi> the Second granted to the Nobles a power of making ſome Laws; but if they under colour of that had made other, they had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded his Prerogative. The Lord Chriſt hath given the Church power to make Laws of <hi>Execution;</hi> but if
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:60567:43"/>ſhe go beyond her Line, and make Laws of <hi>Inſtitution,</hi> ſhe ſeems to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croach upon his Royalty.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2dly.</hi> The Ceremonies thus taken do ſeem to <hi>invert the Goſpel.</hi> The Apoſtle tells the <hi>Galatians</hi> that they were <hi>removed to another Goſpel, which was not another; but there were ſome that troubled them, and would pervert the Goſpel of Chriſt,</hi> Gal. 1.6, 7. The word in the Original is not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to <hi>evert,</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to <hi>invert</hi> the Goſpel. They did not deny the Goſpel, but they added the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Ceremonies to it, and ſo inverted it, and made it to be another Goſpel; a Goſpel mixed with <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Ceremonies, being not the ſame with it ſelf in its purity. And as thoſe <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies did invert the Goſpel, ſo do <hi>ours,</hi> tho upon a different reaſon, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert it alſo. Theirs did invert it, as being made <hi>neceſſary to Salvation;</hi> ours do it, as being made <hi>terms of Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</hi> In the pure Goſpel Heaven and Ordinanees do both ſtand open unto men in the Church. The Goſpel is
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:60567:43"/>inverted not only when men are bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out from Heaven, by making other neceſſaries to Salvation than are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red therein, but alſo when men are bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out from Ordinances by making other terms of Communion than are commanded therein. This latter is that which I ſhall explain by Humane In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances. If a Prince grants a Charter of Franchiſes to a perſon, and, as it paſſes the Great Seal, the Chancellor of his own head adds a Condition to the Grant, the Charter is hereby in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted.<note place="margin">Walſ. <hi>Hiſt. fol.</hi> 44.</note> When King <hi>Edward</hi> the Firſt confirmed the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Charters with this addition, <hi>Salvo jure coronae noſtrae,</hi> the Nobles were diſpleaſed, and would not be content, till their Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were confirmed as they were at firſt granted, in an <hi>abſolute</hi> manner. They were ſenſible that a <hi>new modus</hi> might make their Charters look like another thing than indeed they were. If a man covenant or article with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that he ſhall enjoy ſuch a thing, and without orders a Condition be ſuperadded, the Covenant is inverted. When the Emperor <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:60567:44"/>made an Agreement with the Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Thuan. <hi>Hiſt. l.</hi> 5. <hi>fol.</hi> 106.</note> and ſuperadded a Condition that the Duke ſhould be of his Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Duke utterly refuſed it; the addition made the Covenant another thing. If a man make his Will, and the Scribe of his own head add a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to a Legacy, the Will is invert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; hence in the Civil Law the <hi>Falſarius</hi> is greatly puniſhed.<note place="margin">Qui Teſtamentum, amoverit, deleverit, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terleverit, falſum ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerit, legis Corneliae poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nâ damnatur. <hi>Corp. Jur. Civ.</hi>
               </note> If a Law of Grace be made, and the Judge will by his interpretation put a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of his own upon it, the Law is inverted. <hi>Magna Charta</hi> gives unto the Church <hi>omnia ſua jura integra, &amp; libertates illaeſas.</hi> Should a Judge tell Eccleſiaſtical Perſons, that they ſhould have all their Rights and Liberties, but upon a <hi>Condition of his own deviſing;</hi> who would not conclude that the great Charter was <hi>inverted?</hi> In all theſe Inſtances it is not material, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Condition be added to the thing in <hi>writing,</hi> and ſo imbodied with it, or whether it be added to it by <hi>practical uſe;</hi> in both caſes it <hi>inverts</hi>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:60567:44"/>the thing to which it is added. Now the Goſpel is the Grant, Covenant, Teſtament, Law of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt: In and by it he makes over Ordinances freely, abſolutely, to all that will come to them. If men put in their own Conditions, and ſay, you ſhall have Sacraments, but upon theſe or thoſe terms, which are unneceſſary and unrequired by Chriſt, the Goſpel is inverted, and made another thing than it was; an <hi>abſolute free</hi> gift is one thing, and a <hi>limited conditional</hi> one is another. The firſt is the Goſpel in its purity, as it comes from the hands of Chriſt; the laſt is the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel with a mixture, as it is inverted by men. Neither is it material, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that which is added be a <hi>great</hi> thing, or a <hi>little;</hi> a <hi>little</hi> thing, if added as a Condition, inverts it; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it turns an <hi>abſolute free</hi> diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into a <hi>conditional</hi> one. I conclude with that of St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> upon that Text, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.7.<note place="margin">Comment. in <hi>Gal.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>They ſubvert the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel who bring in,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>paululum quiddam, any little new thing into it;</hi> that is, if it be brought in as neceſſary
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:60567:45"/>to Salvation, or as a Condition to any Ordinance of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3dly.</hi> The Ceremonies thus taken do ſeem to be againſt <hi>Chriſtian Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Charity and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</hi> They ſeem to be againſt <hi>Chriſtian Liberty.</hi> The Liberty which we have in Chriſt is a real one. <hi>Omnia</hi> (ſaith <hi>Tertullian</hi>) <hi>imaginaria in ſeculo; All things, even Liberty it ſelf, are imaginary in the world;</hi> but the Liberty which we have in Chriſt is true. Our Chriſtian Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty ſtands in a ſpiritual manumiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, not only from Sin, Satan, Death, but alſo from the <hi>Yoke of Ceremonies.</hi> In the Goſpel we have a double Door open to us, one into Heaven, another into Ordinances, to fit us for that Bleſſed Region; both theſe open Doors were purchaſed by the precious Blood of Chriſt, neither of them may be ſhut by man. The <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, as made <hi>neceſſary to Salvation,</hi> did ſhut the firſt Door, becauſe there more things were made neceſſary to Salvation than the Goſpel made. Our Ceremonies, as made <hi>terms of Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> ſeem to ſhut the ſecond Door,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:60567:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>becauſe thereby other Conditions of participation in Ordinances are put upon men than are to be found in the Goſpel. A free acceſs unto the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments was not only purchaſed by Chriſt's precious Blood for us, but granted by his Evangelical Charter to us; and a choice, a rare Liberty it is; but if men may bar up, or conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate this acceſs, where is our Chriſtian Liberty? How can we come to Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the Freemen of Chriſt? The Human Yoke of Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies is upon us; and I wonder that it can enter into rational minds, that God ſhould break off the Yoke of <hi>his own Ceremonies,</hi> as unſuitable to the Evangelical Liberty, and yet that a <hi>Yoke of Human Ceremonies</hi> ſhould be put on as congruous to it. If Human Ceremonies may ſucceed in the room of Divine, then the Yoke is not <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved,</hi> but <hi>changed,</hi> and that as much for the worſe, as Human Ceremonies weigh heavier than Divine. Were it put to the option of any intelligent man, whether he would have a Ritual Burthen of <hi>God</hi>'s binding laid upon
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:60567:46"/>him, or one of <hi>Man</hi>'s: He would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly chuſe to have it done rather by the God of Wiſdom and Mercy, than by any Creature. We ſee clearly that God hath no where in the <hi>New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> laid any ſuch burthens, or ſet any ſuch conditional bars to Ordinances; and how, or why ſhould man do it? Or if he do it, how or which way is the <hi>Chriſtian Franchiſe</hi> preſerved? The Church's Power is but ſubordinate, and ſubalternate to Chriſt, and how can it put bars or conditions to that Priviledge which he hath granted to Chriſtians? When a Church uſeth its Power according to the line and level of Scripture, then all is well; but when it overflows, and exceeds its Commiſſion, then Chriſtian Liberty goes to wreck.</p>
            <p>Again, They ſeem to be againſt <hi>Chriſtian Charity,</hi> as being ſtumbling-blocks to doubting Souls, occaſioning their fall into ſin. Our Dear Lord Jeſus left us the Sacraments pure, Divine, altogether free from any ſcruple. But now the myſtical Ceremonies are ſo interwoven and coupled in uſe with
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:60567:46"/>them, that Scrupulous Chriſtians, in partaking of that which Chriſt inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, run into that which Conſcience ſcruples; and in following that which is lifted up in the Example of Pious and Learned Church-men, fall and wound their Souls. The law of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity puts a reſtraint upon indifferent things in the caſe of Scandal. <hi>It is good neither to eat fleſh, nor to drink wine, nor to do any thing whereby thy brother ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth, or is offended, or is made weak,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.21. Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent things are in charity to be abſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from in caſe of ſcandal. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle preſſeth this by very weighty Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments. <hi>The kingdom of God is not meat and drink,</hi> v. 17. Religion doth not ſtand in ſuch things. We muſt not in ſuch things <hi>grieve or deſtroy our bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> v. 15. We muſt not for them <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the work of God,</hi> v. 20. that is, our Brother's Soul, which is his work by way of eminency. We muſt not <hi>deſtroy him for whom Chriſt died,</hi> v. 15. Scandal in indifferent things is not a wounding only, but a killing of our Brother, a kind of Soul-murther. Now if indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:60567:47"/>things, in caſe of ſcandal, are not to be admitted in common uſe, much leſs are thoſe things (which have <hi>ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em mali,</hi> an appearance of evil) in ſuch caſe to be admitted into holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; thither we come by Chriſt's ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, not to grieve and wound, but comfort and heal our Souls. Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſhould not ſuffer any Stumbling-block or Scandal to be ſeen there, every thing there ſhould miniſter comfort and edification. I know many Anſwers are given to this, but ſcarce any ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory ones. 'Tis ſaid, that in caſe of <hi>ſcandal</hi> we muſt abſtain from indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent things, whilſt they <hi>remain indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent,</hi> but not <hi>after they are determined by Authority.</hi> But to me it ſounds ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding harſh, to ſay, that in caſe the Magiſtrate commands it, we may wound or deſtroy our Brother. A Scandal in its nature is ſpiritual Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which no Command of Man can make tolerable. Avoiding of Scandal is a main duty of Charity, which no Command of Man can diſpence with. 'Tis ſaid, that <hi>in conforming to the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, there can be only a ſcandal to a
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:60567:47"/>brother, but in nonconforming there is ſcandal to the Magiſtrate;</hi> and this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed (if it be a Scandal <hi>of the ſame kind,</hi> is greater than the other. But (as Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Mr. <hi>Jeans</hi> doth diſtinguiſh.)<note place="margin">Schol. &amp; Pract Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin. <hi>par 2. fol. 127.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>There is a two-fold acception of Scandal, prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and ſecundary; primary ſcandal is the occaſioning the fall of another into ſin. Secondary is the angring and diſpleaſing of another.</hi> Conformity to the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies occaſions our Brother to fall into ſin, Nonconformity only occaſions the diſpleaſure of the Magiſtrate. Now to diſpleaſe the Magiſtrate is ſurely more tolerable, than to occaſion the pooreſt man to fall into ſin. This is clear, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is more dangerous to diſpleaſe God than Man. 'Tis ſaid further, <hi>Debts of Juſtice are to be paid before debts of Charity: Obedience to Superiors is a debt of Juſtice, a matter of right; but the not giving of offence is a debt of Charity, a matter of courteſy.</hi> But as Mr. <hi>Jeans</hi> hath <hi>fully</hi> anſwered, <hi>The Rule muſt be underſtood,</hi> caeteris paribus, <hi>when the terms of compariſon are equal;</hi> and equal they are not, when the <hi>Minims of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice</hi> are put into the Ballance with the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:60567:48"/>
               <hi>weightieſt duties of Charity;</hi> and ſo 'tis in the preſent compariſon. Of what im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance is the practiſe of a Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, in compariſon of not ſcandalizing our Brother? Who can imagine that the command of a Ceremony can bear proportion with the command of not deſtroying a Brother? The Commands of God touching the externals of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, are to give way to Mercy. <hi>I will have mercy, and not ſacrifice, ſaith God,</hi> Hoſ. 6.6. much more muſt the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of Men do ſo. Beſides, the care of not giving offence, tho <hi>to my Brother,</hi> it be but <hi>a debt of Charity,</hi> yet in regard <hi>of God,</hi> it is a <hi>debt of Juſtice;</hi> and woe to him through whom the offence cometh. Moreover, it is ſaid, that <hi>the offence by the Ceremonies is only</hi> Scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum acceptum, non datum, <hi>a Scanal taken, not given.</hi> But the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies being not merely things indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent but having at leaſt an appearance of evil, the Scandal is not <hi>taken</hi> only, but <hi>given.</hi> It is certainly our duty to abſtain from all appearance of evil. The <hi>Nazarite</hi> was to abſtain from the very Husk of the Grape. The Young
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:60567:48"/>man was not to come nigh the door of the ſtrange Woman. <hi>Secundus</hi> will not deliver a little uſeleſs ſtuff to ſave his life, leſt he ſhould ſeem to be a Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor. <hi>Valentinian</hi> would not endure a little drop of Paganiſh Holy water. We muſt not dwell in the confines or neighbourhood of Sin. We ſhould put away every ſhadow of Will-worſhip, every ſemblance of an addition to the holy Ordinances, every thing that looks like a conformity to the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church; this were the way to be pure from giving offence to our Brethren.</p>
            <p>Moreover, they ſeem to be againſt <hi>Chriſtian <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</hi> The firſt ſtep to that firſt ſin which brought in enmity into the World, was an addition to God's Word. Ye ſhall not <hi>touch it,</hi> Gen. 3.3. This was that that divided God's An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ient People the <hi>Jews,</hi> the <hi>Karai</hi> adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed to the pure Scripture, but the <hi>Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>udici</hi> brought in their Human Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and cried them up as <hi>Lux illa <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>agna, the great Light.</hi> The <hi>Phariſees</hi> would have above the Law their own Ceremonies and Traditions, and ſo they came to ſeparate and divide
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:60567:49"/>themſelves from others, calling the common people <hi>populum terrae, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the earth;</hi> and ſaying to Sinners, ne attingas me, <hi>touch me not.</hi> The <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Ceremonies <hi>troubled</hi> the <hi>Galatians,</hi> Gal. 1.7. <hi>Circumciſion</hi> ceaſing to be Divine any longer, became <hi>Conciſion,</hi> renting the Church; and the Doctors that mixed it with the Goſpel, were as <hi>Dogs,</hi> tearing aſunder the unity of it. When <hi>Victor</hi> urged a neceſſity of conformity in the obſervation of <hi>Eaſter-day, Irenaeus</hi> reproves him for this, <hi>tanquam pacis perturbatorem, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> troubler of the Churches peace;</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed there was a horrible breach be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> and <hi>Weſtern</hi> Churches about it. When Images, a mere Human Invention, were brought into the Church, what fierce Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were there about it? The <hi>Green</hi> Emperors, <hi>Leo Iſaurus, Constantinu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and others, oppoſing them in the <hi>Eaſt.</hi> And on the other ſide, the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of <hi>Rome, Gregory</hi> the Second <hi>Gregory</hi> the Third, and others ſtiſh upholding them in the <hi>Weſt.</hi> In the Council at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> they were ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:60567:49"/>condemned;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Spond.</hi> Ann, Anno Dom. <hi>754. Crab.</hi> Conc. Tom. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> and the people cried out, <hi>hodie ſalus mundo.</hi> In the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> they were advanced again even to veneration; and <hi>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius,</hi> for ſpeaking againſt them, is ſaid to be delivered over to a reprobate mind, and his Books are anathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed. What an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a vehement Contention was there between the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Churches about <hi>le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vened and unlevened bread</hi> in the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt; the <hi>Greeks</hi> calling the <hi>Latins Azymitae,</hi> and the <hi>Latins</hi> the <hi>Greeks, Fermentarii.</hi> Ceremonies and Human Inventions in Worſhip, however they may be intended for Unity, are the occaſions of Contention. Hence <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancton,</hi> tho he conformed to the Rites and Ceremonies in the <hi>Interim,</hi> yet wiſhed with tears that they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, becauſe as long as they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained there would be contention in the Church; and the reaſon of this is evident, The minds of men are not all alike, or of an equal temper. Some Pious and Learned Men allow of Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, other Pious and Learned Men cannot receive them: In ſuch a
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:60567:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>caſe as this,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anſelm.</hi> ad querelas Vaeler auni, fol. <hi>149.</hi>
               </note> the urging of Uniformity is the loſs of Unity. <hi>Anſelm</hi> enquiring whence the various Cuſtoms in the Church aroſe, gives this Anſwer. <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil aliud intelligo quam humanorum ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuum diverſitates. I know nothing but this, that men have different ſentiments of things;</hi> that which one man thinks very apt in the Worſhip of God, that another thinks is not ſo. When ſuch a neceſſary thing as Unity is placed in unneceſſaries, it is loſt; but when it is placed in things like it ſelf, I mean in neceſſary things, then it is preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. The Apoſtles (who as well un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, and as much deſired Unity in the Church as any) would <hi>lay no other burthen on Christians than ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary things,</hi> Act. 15.28. St. <hi>Paul</hi> lays down a great many Unities, <hi>One body, one ſpirit, one hope, one Lord, one faith, one baptiſm, one God and father of all.</hi> Eph. 4.4, 5, 6. but there is not a word of <hi>one Ceremony.</hi> Thoſe Biſhops took the right courſe for Unity, who being met together in Council, made a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non which they called <hi>Adiaphoron,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Socrat. <hi>Hiſt. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 20.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they left the obſervation of
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:60567:50"/>
               <hi>Eaſter-day</hi> indifferent, as men would themſelves. Were indifferent things left in their indifferency, the Unity of the Church would be much greater than it is.</p>
            <p>Thus much may ſuffice touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Ceremonies; only becauſe there are two Pleas for their innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, I muſt conſider them.</p>
            <p>The one is this; The Ceremonies are only for <hi>decency and order,</hi> and ſo within that Apoſtolical Precept, <hi>Let all things be done decently, and in order,</hi> 1 Cor. 14.40.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, Were the Ceremonies within that Precept, I ſhould beg my pardon, and pronounce them innocent; but I take it they are not within it, and to clear this, I offer theſe things.</p>
            <p>The Evangelical Sacraments, which are God's own Ceremonies, are in themſelves, and without any Human dreſs, worthy of all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence,<note place="margin">Noſtra Sacramenta tam praeclara ſunt, ut etiamſi nuda &amp; nullis Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentalibus ſuffulta pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponerentur, omni eſſent veneratione digna. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dina in <hi>Aquin.</hi> 1, 2. <hi>Q.</hi> 108. <hi>Art.</hi> 2.</note> the Inſtitution hath put a glory upon them. Human Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, which are as much below them, as a Cloud is
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:60567:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>below the Sun, are more apt to darken than illuſtrate them. When Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are in their pure ſimplicity, then the ſplendour of the Holy Signs ſhines forth; but when they are muffled up in Human Rites, then the Divine Beauty is obſcured. And if Divine Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies need Human to put a deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum upon them, much more do Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Ceremonies need an addition of further Ceremonies for that end, and ſo there may be Ceremonies upon Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies in <hi>infinitum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Lord Chriſt, who knew better than all men what Decency is, never inſtituted any ſuch Ceremonies. The Apoſtles, who gave the Rule of Decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, never uſed them. They did admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Ordinances decently, but without them. Hence it appears that their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept never extended to them; for had it done ſo, they would not have omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them, but had practiſed that Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept which they had given. The Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the Apoſtles, which was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Ceremonies, was either decent, or undecent, (for Decency and Undecen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy are <hi>privatively oppoſite,</hi> and between
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:60567:51"/>privative oppoſites there is no <hi>medium of abnegation in ſubjecto capaci.</hi>) If the Apoſtles Worſhip, void of all Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, be decent, then Decency doth not conſiſt in Ceremonies; if undecent, they did not (which cannot be imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned) obſerve their own Rule of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, and act as they taught.</p>
            <p>Order and Decency in the Worſhip of God are things neceſſary, not mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by a <hi>poſitive</hi> Law, but by a <hi>natural.</hi> Not only the Apoſtolical Precept, but the very <hi>dictate of Nature</hi> is, that the Service of God ſhould be performed in an orderly and decent manner. The Heathen Oracle could ſay, That in the Worſhip of God men ſhould follow, <hi>morem optimum, the beſt manner.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nat. Quaeſt. l. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca</hi> out of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> tells us, That when men have to do with the Gods, they ſhould be, <hi>verecundiores &amp; compoſiti, modeſt and compoſed in their demeanour.</hi> The Light of Nature teacheth us, that we ſhould ſerve God in a way ſuitable and congruous to his Divine Majeſty. Thus Order and Decency are neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but ſo are not Ceremonies. Hence it appears, that the difference between
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:60567:52"/>them is as great, as between neceſſary and unneceſſary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Order</hi> is nothing but a right diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of things, <hi>Decency</hi> is nothing but the ſeemlineſs of Order. Order and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency require not,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide</hi> Ames Medul. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 13.</note> that ſome Holy things ſhould be newly ordained; but that thoſe which are ordained by God, ſhould be uſed in a way congruous to their dignity. The Ceremonies, which are new Appointments, appertain not to Order and Decency. The inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſomewhat new is one thing; and the right and ſeemly diſpoſition of that which is inſtituted, is another.</p>
            <p>The other Plea is this. The Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies are not made by our Church <hi>any parts of Worſhip,</hi> and therefore there is no offence in them.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, The Ceremonies ſeem to be parts of Worſhip feveral ways. They ſeem to be parts of Worſhip <hi>in themſelves,</hi> as being an honouring of God, at leaſt in ſome reſpect. It's true they are not parts of Worſhip, <hi>ratione principii,</hi> becauſe they are not parts of <hi>Divine Inſtitution:</hi> But they ſeem to be parts of Worſhip, <hi>ratione termini</hi>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:60567:52"/>as being an honour done to God. There may be a double honour done to God. There is an honour done to him as the Supream Being, by ſubjection and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation: And there is an honour done to him as the Fountain of Grace, by dependance upon him for ſome Spiritual Gift. Both theſe ſeem to be in the uſe of the Ceremonies. In the uſe of the Croſs, the Infant is reſigned to God, <hi>dedicated</hi> to him that died on the Croſs, and this looks like Worſhip. Again, the Ceremonies are <hi>Myſtical Teachers;</hi> not <hi>Supream Teachers,</hi> for that were to turn them into Idols; but <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder Teachers;</hi> and therefore in the regular uſe of them we muſt depend upon the great Teacher for illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and this alſo ſeems to be an act of Worſhip.</p>
            <p>They ſeem to be parts of Worſhip <hi>relatively,</hi> as they are in conjunction with the holy things of God. The Croſs is ſo interwoven with Baptiſm in the adminiſtration of it, that it looks like a part of it. Before Baptiſm the Miniſter prays for thoſe that are dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to God; and that <hi>dedication</hi> is, as
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:60567:53"/>the Canon tells us, <hi>by the Croſs.</hi> After Baptiſm, thanks are given that the Child is received into the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and this is done by the <hi>Croſs</hi> alſo: For upon making the <hi>Croſs,</hi> the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſaith, <hi>We receive this Child into the Congregation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Parker</hi> Of the Croſs <hi>fol.</hi> 115.</note> Thus, as Mr. <hi>Parker</hi> hath noted, the <hi>Croſs</hi> is <hi>incorporated</hi> into Baptiſm in the adminiſtration of it. They are knit together, <hi>à priori &amp; à poſteriori,</hi> by the precedent and ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Prayers.</p>
            <p>Moreover, they ſeem to be parts of Worſhip <hi>reputatively,</hi> as they are high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly valued. Our Saviour charges the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> that they preferred their <hi>Traditions</hi> above the Commands of God, <hi>Matt.</hi> 15.3, 6, 9. Their <hi>Corban</hi> ſwallowed up their duty to Parents. The <hi>Jews</hi> ſay, that <hi>there is more in the words of the Scribes, than in the words of the Law; and that it were better to die, than to violate a Tradition.</hi> Our Divines charge the very ſame thing upon the Papiſts. <hi>Whitaker</hi> tells <hi>Duraeus,</hi> That it was a greater Offence,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tom</hi> 1.206.</note> 
               <hi>Quadrageſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam violare quam Dei verbum contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere, to break Lent, than to deſpiſe the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:60567:53" rendition="simple:additions"/>Word of God. Gregorius Hemburgius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Melch. Adam.</hi> de vitis Jure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſulto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</note> Doctor of Law, was wont to ſay, That for many years men might ſpeak more freely, <hi>de poteſtate Dei quàm Papae, of the Power of God, than of the Pope.</hi> And what is the value that is now upon Ceremonies among our ſelves? Hath there not been too high a rate ſet upon them? May we not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain in the words of St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. <hi>75.</hi> ad <hi>Pomp.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vina praecepta ſolvit, &amp; praeterit humana traditio. Human Tradition diſſolves and paſſes over Divine Precepts?</hi> It is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, that if <hi>Learning and Piety</hi> could have <hi>outweighed a Ceremony,</hi> many Worthy and Excellent Perſons had been now in the Church, who are at this time out of it. I may add, it is alſo clear, that if that Heat and Zeal which hath run out againſt <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformity,</hi> could have been turned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Impiety</hi> and <hi>Profaneneſs,</hi> we had now been a much more excellent Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple than at this time we are. It was often the complaint of <hi>Eraſmus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Whit. <hi>Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>fol.</hi> 726.</note> 
               <hi>Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na contemni, Humana urgeri. That Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine things were contemned, and Human urged.</hi> If this ſhould be our caſe, it
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:60567:54"/>would be no wonder at all for men to ſay, that the Ceremonies are made <hi>parts of Worſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much touching the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies: And if what hath been alledged againſt them be true, the Separation of the Nonconformiſts can hardly be imagined to be <hi>without cauſe.</hi> But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe not only the Ceremonies, but ſome <hi>other terms</hi> lay as blocks in their way; I ſhall add one ſhort word more. They were by an <hi>Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> deprived of their People, and their People of them. They could not come up to the terms of a publick Miniſtry, neither would their People come to the publick Ordinances; in this, which I take it, was their caſe, it is extream hard to charge criminous Schiſm up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them. When the Emperor put <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> out of his Church,<note place="margin">Socrat. <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 16.</note> the <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>annites</hi> ſeparated from the Publick, and thoſe not only People, but Biſhops and Presbyters; yet I do not know that they were charged with the crime of Schiſm for it.<note place="margin">Theod. <hi>l</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 21.</note> When <hi>Euſtathius</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Antioch</hi> was baniſhed, many people and Miniſters left the Publick
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:60567:54"/>Aſſemblies. Yet I find not that theſe Separations were charged with the crime of Schiſm. The Nonconformiſts being in the ſame, or a very like caſe, Charity would make the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of them. Thus much touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſixth Character. Now I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the laſt.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7thly.</hi> Schiſmatical Separation is not only from a particular Church, but from the <hi>Catholick</hi> one. It is a memorable Paſſage of the Reverend <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> whoſe words I ſhall tranſcribe. <hi>Neither particular Perſons,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King. 1624.</note> 
               <hi>nor particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Churches, are to work as ſeveral di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided Bodies by themſelves</hi> (which is the ground of all Schiſm) <hi>but are to teach, and to be taught, and to do all other Chriſtian Duties, as parts conjoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the whole, and Members of the ſame Commonwealth or Corporation.</hi> The Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent <hi>Davenant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Boroughs <hi>in his</hi> Ireni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum. fol. <hi>67.</hi>
               </note> in his Rules for Peace, ſaith, <hi>Proſcindi nec debent nec poſſunt à communione particularium Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiarum, quae manent conjunctae cum Eccleſiâ Catholicâ; Thoſe may not be cut off from communion with particular Churches, who remain joined to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:60567:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>Church.</hi> I may add, Thoſe may not be eſteemed Schiſmaticks by any particular Church, who are in conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with the Univerſal. Schiſmatical Separation is not only from a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Church, but from the Univerſal. And is it thus with the Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts? Do they ſeparate from the Church-Catholick? I take it they do not; and for this I ſhall lay down two or three things.</p>
            <p>A Particular Church may be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered two ways, either in that which it hath in <hi>common with other particular Churches,</hi> now, or heretofore in being; or in that which it hath <hi>particular to it ſelf.</hi> A particular Church in the <hi>firſt reſpect</hi> acts as a part of the Church-Catholick; but in the <hi>ſecond reſpect</hi> it acts by it ſelf. A Separation from a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church, conſidered in the <hi>firſt reſpect,</hi> is a ſeparation from the Church Catholick; but a ſeparation from it, conſidered in the <hi>ſecond reſpect,</hi> is not ſo. The Nonconformiſts differ from our Church, not in that which it hath in <hi>common with other Churches,</hi> but in that which it hath in <hi>peculiar.</hi> They differ
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:60567:55"/>from it in <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> ſo do the Foreign Churches; they differ from its <hi>Liturgy,</hi> ſo do the Foreign Churches, at leaſt in part. Their Congregations are <hi>diſtinct, and diſtant from the Parochial Churches,</hi> ſo is one Parochial Church from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. If the Foreign Churches, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſuch differences, are in unity with our Church, ſo are the Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts. If the Nonconformiſts, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſuch differences are Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, what are the Foreign Churches which have the ſame? You will ſay the caſe is diferent. Thoſe of Foreign Churches never did, as our Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts do, go out from our Parochial Churches. Very true, but every <hi>local</hi> ſeparation doth not amount to Schiſm; neither have others the ſame occaſion of ſeparation from our Churches as the Nonconformiſts have.</p>
            <p>When a <hi>Law or Canon</hi> made by thoſe who have particular juriſdiction in a Nation or Church, will juſtify Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and make it no Schiſm, then the Separation is not from the Church-Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick. But ſuch is the caſe of the Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts. Should there be ſuch a
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:60567:56"/>
               <hi>Law or Canon</hi> made among us, it would juſtify their Separation, and make it no Schiſm; therefore their Separation is not from the Church Catholick.</p>
            <p>When men ſeparate from a Church in pride, and contempt, as if <hi>they only</hi> were the Church, then the Separation is from the Church Catholick. Thus the <hi>Novatians</hi> thought that the pure Church was with them only. Thus the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> ſaid, that the Church was only in <hi>parte Donati.</hi> Thus the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſay, that the Church is only in <hi>parte Papae:</hi> but the Nonconformiſts do not do ſo. They acknowledge our Church to be a true Church, they are joined to it in all that which is true unity. They would further bear a part in it, if ſome Stumbling blocks were out of the way. By theſe things it may appear, that they ſtill remain in conjunction with the Church-Catholick.</p>
            <p>Thus I have gone over the Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters of Schiſmatical Separation; and in ſo doing have briefly examined the Caſe of the Nonconformiſts.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:60567:56"/>
            <head>Books Printed for, and Sold by <hi>Thomas Cockerill,</hi> at the <hi>Three Legs</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey,</hi> near <hi>Stocks-Market.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HIſtorical Collections, the 3d Part, in 2 Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes. Never before Printed; Containing the Principal Matters which happened from the meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Parliament, <hi>November</hi> the 3d. 1640. to the end of the Year 1644. wherein is a particular Account of the Riſe and Progreſs of the Civil War to that Period: Impartially related. Setting forth only Matter of Fact in Order of Time, without Obſervation or Reflection. By <hi>John Ruſhworth,</hi> Fol.</p>
            <p>A Demonſtration of the firſt Applications of the <hi>Apocalypſe,</hi> together with the Conſent of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients concerning the Fourth Beaſt in the 7th of <hi>Daniel,</hi> and the Beaſt in the <hi>Revelations.</hi> By <hi>Drue Creſcener,</hi> D. D. 4t<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>A Seaſonable Diſcourſe, wherein is examined what is lawful, during the Confuſions and Revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Government. Stitched. 4t<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>The Evidence of Things not ſeen: or divers Spiritual and Philoſophical Diſcourſes concerning the ſtate of Holy Men after Death; By that emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently Learned Divine, <hi>Moſes Amyraldus.</hi> Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of the <hi>French</hi> Tongue by a Miniſter of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> 8v<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>A Succinct and Seaſonable Diſcourſe of the Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, Cauſes, Nature, Riſe, Growth and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies of <hi>mental Errors.</hi> To which is added, 1.) An Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Gary</hi> againſt Infant-Baptiſm. 2) An Anſwer to ſome <hi>Antinomian</hi> Errors. (3) A Sermon about Union. By <hi>John Flavel.</hi> 8v<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe concerning Liturgies, by the late learned Divine Mr. <hi>David Clerkſon.</hi> 8v<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:60567:57"/>
               <hi>Geography Anatomized:</hi> Or, A Compleat Geogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phical Grammar, being a ſhort and exact Analyſis of the whole body of Modern Geography; after a new, plain and eaſy method, whereby any perſon may in a ſhort time attain to the knowledge of that moſt noble and uſeful Science, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To which is ſubjoined the preſent ſtate of the <hi>European</hi> Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Indies;</hi> with a Reaſonable Propoſal for the propagation of the Bleſſed Goſpel in all Pagan Countries. Illuſtrated with divers Maps. By <hi>Patrick Gordon,</hi> M. A. 8v<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>An Expoſition of the Aſſemblies Shorter Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm, with Practical Inferences from each Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; by <hi>John Flavell,</hi> late Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Dartmouth</hi> in <hi>Devon.</hi> 8v<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>The Future State: Or, A Diſcourſe attempting ſome diſplay of the Soul's Happineſs, in regard to that eternally progreſſive Knowledge, or eternal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of Knowledge, and the conſequences of it, which is among the Bleſſed in Heaven; by a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey Gentleman, a Worſhipper of God in the way of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>The Death of Miniſters Improved: Or, An Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation to the Inhabitants of <hi>Hortley</hi> in <hi>Gloceſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> and others, on the much lamented death of that Faithful Miniſter Mr. <hi>Henry Stubbs:</hi> To which is added a Sermon upon that occaſion; by <hi>Richard Baxter.</hi> 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>Engliſh Exerciſes for School-boys to tranſlate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Latin; comprizing all the Rules of Grammar, and other neceſſary Obſervations, afcending gradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally from the meaneſt to the higheſt Capacities By <hi>John Garretſon,</hi> School maſter. Fourth Edition. 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>A Short Introduction into Orthography: Or. The method of True Spelling; publiſhed for the common good, but eſpecially for the uſe of a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Grammer and Writing-School. 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:60567:57"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
